GOOD SHOW. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
WELCOME TO THE OCTOBER 21ST 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS .
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT
RANDLEMAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL
PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT
ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE ROMITA SALONI
WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE ROMITA
SHALL ONLY HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW MATERIAL OWNING COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST
PEOPLES. COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE MY ALLEGIANCE TO THE
FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA EXCUSE ME THE REPUBLIC
FOR WHICH STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH
LIBERTY AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> >> AND ON BEHALF OF THE
BOARD I WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F.
GOV TV TODAY PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE TRANSCRIPTS
AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE. >> AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK
WE SHOULD PROBABLY GO TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
>> YES THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS THE APPEARANCE BY THE
HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE. THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD
FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES. >> WELCOME, MR. MAYOR.
DO YOU HAVE ANY OPENING REMARKS?
GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD AND TO MY FRIENDS IN THE AUDIENCE FROM
POTRERO HILL, JUDE. >> WE LOVE YOU DUDE.
CONGRATULATIONS AND AS MAYOR AS MAYOR MY TOP PRIORITY IS
KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO SAFE WHILE ALWAYS ALWAYS UPHOLDING
OUR CITY'S VALUES AND LAWS LED BY LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT WITH
THE SUPPORT FROM THE STATE AND FEDERAL LAW ENFORCEMENT
PARTNERS. WE'VE DRIVEN VIOLENT CRIME DOWN
TO ITS LOWEST LEVELS SINCE THE 1950S AND REDUCED TEN
ENCAMPMENTS TO RECORD LOWS. AND WE ARE SHOWING REAL
PROGRESS. YET THE FENTANYL CRISIS
CONTINUES TO IMPACT OUR STREETS, OUR FAMILIES
AND BUSINESSES. AND MY ADMINISTRATION IS
TACKLING IT HEAD ON. WE'VE WORKED TO TRANSFORM THE
CITY'S RESPONSE TO THIS CRISIS WHILE COORDINATING LOCAL LAW
ENFORCEMENT EFFORTS WITH FBI, DEA, ATF AND THE U.S.
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE TO DISMANTLE OPEN AIR DRUG MARKETS
AND CARTELS THROUGH DEMAK. WHILE I DEEPLY RESPECT OUR
MILITARY SERVICE MEMBERS, THE FEDERALIZED NATIONAL GUARD DOES
NOT HAVE THE AUTHORITY TO ARREST DRUG DEALERS AND DISRUPT
DRUG MARKETS. DEPLOYING THE NATIONAL GUARD IS
CLEARLY NOT THE SOLUTION TO THE CITY'S CHALLENGES.
AS WE TACKLE FENTANYL ALONGSIDE STATE AND FEDERAL LAW
ENFORCEMENT PARTNERS, I WILL NEVER WAVER IN MY COMMITMENT TO
PROTECT THE PEOPLE AND VALUES THAT DEFINE SAN FRANCISCO.
OUR SAFETY, COMPASSION AND SENSE OF COMMUNITY.
AND I WILL DO EVERYTHING EVERYTHING IN MY POWER TO
SUPPORT OUR IMMIGRANT AND LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITIES WHO HAVE
CONTINUOUSLY COME UNDER THREAT .
>> THAT IS WHAT MAKES US SAN FRANCISCO.
AT THE SAME TIME WE MUST CONTINUE THE DAILY WORK OF
GOVERNING AND SUPPORTING OUR CITY'S RECOVERY.
YESTERDAY UNDER THE LEADERSHIP OF CHAIR MELGAR ALONGSIDE
SUPERVISORS MAHMOOD AND CHEN, THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE HELD A HEARING ON MY FAMILY ZONING PLAN WITH MANY OF
THE BOARD MEMBERS OFFERING THOUGHTFUL REMARKS, AMENDMENTS
AND QUESTIONS. AS ALL OF YOU KNOW, THE STATE
IS REQUIRING US TO GO THROUGH THIS PROCESS.
I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR THE MANY HOURS SPENT WITH THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT NEIGHBORS, SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS
AND ADVOCATES OVER THE PAST MANY MONTHS IN SHAPING THIS
IMPORTANT LEGISLATION. I KNOW HOW IMPORTANT THIS WORK
IS AND I KNOW YOU'VE BEEN WORKING HARD ALONGSIDE MANY
OTHERS. TOO MANY PARENTS ARE
QUESTIONING WHETHER THEY CAN AFFORD TO RAISE THEIR CHILDREN
IN SAN FRANCISCO. AND TOO MANY YOUNG PEOPLE ARE
UNSURE IF THEY WILL BE ABLE TO STAY IN THE CITY THEY LOVE OUR
THEM OUR FAMILY ZONING PLAN ADDRESSES THOSE CHALLENGES BY
ADDING MORE HOUSING, SUPPORTING SMALL BUSINESSES AND PRESERVING
WHAT MAKES SAN FRANCISCO UNIQUE ALL WHILE KEEPING LOCAL CONTROL
OVER OUR ZONING DECISIONS RATHER THAN CEDING IT TO
SACRAMENTO. WORKING WITH SUPERVISORS MELGAR
AND SUTTER WE ADDED AMENDMENTS THAT STRENGTHEN THE PLAN'S
PROTECTIONS FOR TENANTS AND SMALL BUSINESSES.
IN THE WEEKS AHEAD MY TEAM AND I WILL CONTINUE REVIEWING
AMENDMENTS TO ENSURE WE ADVANCE A PLAN THAT HELPS FAMILIES
AFFORD TO LIVE HERE AND KEEPS SAN FRANCISCO IN CONTROL OF ITS
FUTURE. THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR
DEDICATION TO THE WORKING PEOPLE, FAMILIES AND SMALL
BUSINESSES ACROSS OUR NEIGHBORHOODS.
THEY ARE COUNTING ON US TO MAKE THIS CITY MORE AFFORDABLE
AND MAINTAIN CONTROL OF OUR ZONING.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING OUR WORK TOGETHER TO
ACCOMPLISH THAT. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE TOPIC FOR DISTRICT 11?
>> YES. THE FIRST TOPICS SUBMITTED BY
THE DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR CHEN IS THE
RECRUITMENT AND RETENTION PRACTICES FOR POLICE DEPARTMENT
TO INCREASE LANGUAGE ETHNIC AND GENDER DIVERSITY.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN YOU MAY ASK YOUR OPENING QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT BENJAMIN.
THANK YOU FOR JOINING US TODAY, MR. MAYOR.
>> I BELIEVE THAT A CORNERSTONE OF OUR PUBLIC SAFETY SOLUTIONS
SHOULD INCLUDE BUILDING A POLICE FORCE THAT REFLECTS THE
COMMUNITY IT SERVES. TO ME THAT INCLUDES FOR EXAMPLE
,THE LINGUISTIC COMPETENCE TO SERVE MONOLINGUAL COMMUNITIES.
>> IT MEANS GENDER PARITY SO THAT WE ARE INCREASING THE
REPRESENTATION OF MEN, POLICE OFFICERS.
>> IT MEANS AN ETHNICALLY DIVERSE POLICE FORCE THAT LOOK
LIKE SAN FRANCISCO AND THAT DIVERSITY NEIGHBORHOOD ACROSS
THE CITY. >> BUT IT ALSO ENSURING THAT
OUR POLICE FORCE POSSESS THE SENSITIVITY AWARENESS, TRAINING
AND PROTOCOLS TO BE RESPONSIVE TO THE CHALLENGE OF OUR LOCAL
COMMUNITIES FACE INCLUDING THE HEIGHTENED ENFORCEMENT OF ICE
RAIDS IN THESE TIMES. >> AS YOU KNOW, THE MORE
DIVERSE OUR LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCIES ARE, THE MORE THAT WE
REFLECT THE MAKEUP OF OUR CITY'S DEMOGRAPHICS AND THE
SAFER AND MORE EFFECTIVE OUR PUBLIC SAFETY INITIATIVE WILL
BE INCLUDING AND ESPECIALLY OUR SANCTUARY CENTRAL VALLEY.
OUR CENTURY CITY POLICIES UPHOLDING AND DEFENDING OUR
CENTURY CITY POLICIES IS THE HEARTS AND MINDS OF MANY OF OUR
CONSTITUENTS. ESPECIALLY GIVEN THE HEIGHTENED
ICE ENFORCEMENT ACTIVITIES TERRORIZING OUR CITY.
>> WHY RECRUITMENT OF OUR OFFICER TO SFPD SEEMS TO BE
TRENDING IN THE HIGH AND RIGHT DIRECTIONS.
>> I'M STILL CONCERNED THAT WE'RE NOT MAKING SIGNIFICANT
PROGRESS ON OUR 30 BY 30 GOALS AND OUR GOALS FOR THE LANGUAGE
AND ETHIC DIVERSITY. WILL YOU COMMIT TO IMMEDIATELY
IMPLEMENTING PROGRAMS THAT HAVE BEEN SUCCESSFUL IN OTHER
COUNTIES AND CITY AND CITIES TO RECRUIT AND RETAIN FEMALE
OFFICERS, OFFICERS OF COLOR AND OFFICERS?
>> WHAT LANGUAGE AND WHAT LANGUAGE COMPETENCY?
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
MAYOR LARRY, YOU MAY RESPOND TO THE OPENING QUESTION.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION, SUPERVISOR CHEN.
WHEN I ISSUED THE REBUILDING THE RANKS EXECUTIVE DIRECTIVE
EARLIER THIS YEAR I SAID I SAID OUR CITY NEEDED A CLEAR
AND IMMEDIATE PLAN TO RESTORE OUR SWORN PUBLIC SAFETY
WORKFORCE. WE NEEDED A PLAN THAT WOULD NOT
ONLY PUT MORE OFFICERS OUT ON OUR STREETS BUT MAKE SURE THOSE
OFFICERS REFLECT THE CITY THAT THEY SERVE.
>> THIS INITIATIVE IS ABOUT REBUILDING CAPACITY AND GAINING
TRUST THROUGH REFORMS THAT WILL HELP KEEP OUR COMMUNITIES SAFE
BY MAKING SURE OUR POLICE DEPARTMENT HAS THE STAFF
AND SUPPORT IT NEEDS TO DO ITS JOB SAFELY AND EFFECTIVELY.
TO DATE SAN FRANCISCO HAS SEEN A NET INCREASE IN POLICE
OFFICERS AND SHERIFF'S DEPUTIES FOR THE FIRST TIME IN A DECADE
WITH ENTRY LEVEL POLICE OFFICER APPLICATIONS UP 40% AND AN
ACADEMY GRADUATION RATE UP 20%. BUT AS YOU MENTIONED, STAFFING
ALONE IS NOT ENOUGH. WE NEED TO REBUILD THE RANKS
WITH PURPOSE TO CREATE A MODERN PROFESSIONAL AND INCLUSIVE
POLICE DEPARTMENT ONE THAT DRAWS ON THE DIVERSITY, THE
LANGUAGES AND THE LIVED EXPERIENCES OF THE PEOPLE THAT
LIVE AND WORK AND PLAY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THANK YOU, MAYOR LURIE. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN YOU MAY NOW
ASK A FOLLOW UP QUESTION DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE OPENING
QUESTION. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT AGAIN.
>> MAY I CAN YOU PLEASE SPECIFY A KIND A KIND OF PROGRAMING
THAT OUT YOUR DEPARTMENT IS CONSIDERED BRING IN HELP TO
BUILD A CULTURAL COMPETENCY INCLUDING THE TRAININGS, THE
AWARENESS AND THE PORTAL COURSE AROUND SAYS SENSITIVE ISSUES
ESPECIALLY THIS TIMES RELATING TO ICE ENFORCEMENT
AND SANCTUARY CITY POLICIES. >> MAYOR LEARY YOU MAY NOW
RESPOND TO THE FOLLOW UP QUESTION.
SUPERVISOR S.F. PD IS RECRUITMENT UNIT CONDUCTS
EXTENSIVE OUTREACH TO RECRUIT PEOPLE WHO REFLECT THE
COMMUNITIES THAT IT SERVES. THE EMPHASIS IS ON RECRUITING
OUTREACH TO DIVERSE COMMUNITY AND EDUCATIONAL PARTNERS
AND STAYING ENGAGED WITH APPLICANTS BEYOND THE INITIAL
HIRING CONTACT THROUGH MULTILINGUAL ADVERTISING
IN CHINESE, SPANISH AND SO MANY OTHER LANGUAGES.
AS CPD HIGHLIGHTS BILINGUAL OFFICERS.
TO SHOW THAT IF YOU SPEAK THE LANGUAGE OF SAN FRANCISCO
THERE'S A PLACE FOR YOU IN THE DEPARTMENT BECAUSE
UNDERSTANDING OUR COMMUNITIES AS YOU POINTED OUT IS ESSENTIAL
TO KEEPING THEM SAFE AS CPD IS EQUALLY COMMITTED TO GENDER
REPRESENTATION AND WAS AMONG THE FIRST MAJOR POLICE
DEPARTMENTS TO SIGN THE NATIONAL 30 BY 30 PLEDGE.
BUT WE STILL HAVE WORK TO DO. WE ARE COMMITTED TO SPECIFIC
ACTIONS TO SUPPORT AND ADVANCE WOMEN IN LAW ENFORCEMENT.
BEYOND THAT THE DEPARTMENT HAS WORKED TO STRENGTHEN FAMILY
SUPPORT POLICIES, EXPAND MEMBERSHIP MENTORSHIP
OPPORTUNITIES AND ENSURE TRANSPARENT MERIT BASED SYSTEMS
THAT HELP ALL MEMBERS GROW AND LEAD.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT REBUILDING THE RANKS, IT'S NOT JUST ABOUT
STAFFING. IT'S ABOUT BUILDING A
DEPARTMENT THAT REFLECTS OUR CITY BY RECRUITING FASTER
TRAINING SMARTER AND SUPPORTING OFFICERS TO SERVE SAN
FRANCISCO'S DIVERSE COMMUNITIES WITH INTEGRITY.
>> THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR. >> MAYOR LURIE, YOU MAY NOW ASK
A QUESTION TO SUPERVISOR CHEN OR TO ANY OTHER SUPERVISOR
IN ATTENDANCE PERTAINING TO THE SAME TOPIC BUT NOT NECESSARILY
RELATED TO THE PREVIOUS QUESTION.
OKAY. THE MAYOR.
THE MAYOR IS GOOD. >> I SEE SUPERVISOR FIELDER
IN THE QUEUE. SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU SO
MUCH PRESIDENT MILLMAN. >> THANK YOU MAYOR LURIE FOR
BEING HERE TODAY. COLLEAGUES, I WOULD LIKE TO
MAKE A MOTION TO ASK ALL OF YOU TO PROVIDE ME THE OPPORTUNITY
TO ASK AN UNSCHEDULED QUESTION TO THE MAYOR TODAY.
>> AND FOLLOWING THE RECOMMENDATION OF THE CITY
ATTORNEY I WILL EXPLAIN HOW MY QUESTION IS ALLOWABLE BY
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTION TWO POINT 11.
>> FIRSTLY, I AM AN ELIGIBLE SUPERVISOR THAT IS A SUPERVISOR
WHO COULD HAVE SUBMITTED A TOPIC IN ADVANCE TODAY.
SECONDLY, THERE HAS BEEN A SUDDEN OR UNEXPECTED INCIDENT
OR OCCURRENCE AND THAT IS PRESIDENT DONALD TRUMP MAKING
NOT ONE BUT TWO STATEMENTS COMMITTING TO SEND THE NATIONAL
GUARD TO SAN FRANCISCO. SINCE LAST WEDNESDAY AFTERNOON
THE REASON COULD THAT THIS COULD NOT HAVE BEEN ANTICIPATED
BEFORE NOON LAST WEDNESDAY IS BECAUSE I DO NOT HAVE ANY LINE
OF COMMUNICATION WITH THE PRESIDENT.
>> I DON'T HAVE TELEPATHIC CAPABILITIES TO HAVE
ANTICIPATED HE WOULD HAVE MADE THOSE STATEMENTS.
>> THIRDLY, MEMBERS OF THE BOARD COULD NOT HAVE
ANTICIPATED THAT INCIDENT AT NOON LAST WEDNESDAY AS THE
FIRST REPORTS OF TRUMP'S STATEMENTS WERE MADE WEDNESDAY
AFTERNOON PACIFIC TIME POLITICO ACTUALLY FIRST REPORTED ON
WEDNESDAY AT 143 PACIFIC TIME. >> FOURTHLY, THE INCIDENT OR
OCCURRENCE RAISES FORMAL TIME SENSITIVE POLICY MATTERS WITHIN
THE SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION OF THE MAYOR AS THE MAYOR HAS
BOTH THE PERMISSION TO ASK THE GOVERNOR TO SEND THE NATIONAL
GUARD AND ALSO AS LAID OUT IN ARTICLE THREE OF THE CITY
CHARTER SECTION 3.100 QUOTE THE MAYOR SHALL HAVE RESPONSE
ABILITY FOR ONE GENERAL GENERAL ADMINISTRATION AND OVERSIGHT OF
ALL DEPARTMENTS AND GOVERNMENTAL UNITS IN THE
EXECUTIVE BRANCH OF THE CITY AND COUNTY TO COORDINATION OF
ALL INTERGOVERNMENTAL ACTIVITIES OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY. AND MY QUESTION PERTAINS TO
BOTH THE NATIONAL GUARD AND COORDINATION OF
INTERGOVERNMENTAL ACTIVITIES OF THE CITY AND COUNTY.
>> FIFTHLY, THE QUESTION CANNOT BE ADEQUATELY ADDRESSED AT THE
MAYOR'S NEXT SCHEDULED APPEARANCE BECAUSE WE MAY VERY
WELL HAVE THE NATIONAL GUARD ON OUR FOOTSTEPS AND THIS IS NOT
BEEN CONSIDERED IN COMMITTEE AND IS NOT ON THE BOARD'S
AGENDA FOR TODAY. SO WITH THAT I ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT IN ASKING AN UNSKILLED SCHEDULED QUESTION SUPERVISOR
FIELDER HAS MADE A MOTION TO BE ALLOWED TO ASK AN UNSCHEDULED
QUESTION. I AM SEEING A SECOND FROM
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. IS THERE ANY DISCUSSION?
>> I DON'T KNOW IF YOU I DON'T KNOW IF YOU GET TO TALK I WILL.
I AM THE DESIGNATED GRINCH OF THIS BODY.
IT IS MY JOB OR PARTLY MY JOB TO PREVENT US FROM STRETCHING
OUR RULES TO THE POINT WHERE WE ARE NOT FOLLOWING THEM
GENERALLY. AND I DO THINK THAT THERE IS A
SIGNIFICANT RISK IN SLIPPERY SLOPES AND DOING SOMETHING ONCE
AND THEN CONTINUING TO HAVE AN EXPECTATION FROM SUPERVISORS
THAT THEY'LL BE ABLE TO DO IT FOR OTHER TOPICS AND ON FUTURE
OCCASIONS. SO I WOULD GENERALLY BE
INCLINED TO VOTE NO ON A REQUEST LIKE THIS.
>> HOWEVER, IF HOWEVER THE MAYOR HAS INDICATED THAT HE
WOULD LIKE TO BE GIVEN THE OPPORTUNITY TO ANSWER THIS
QUESTION AND SO I WILL STAND DOWN FROM MY GRINCH LEANINGS
AND SUPPORT THE MOTION. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO ALLOW SUPERVISOR FIELDER TO ASK
THE QUESTION? THIS IS AN EIGHT VOTE THRESHOLD
SUPERVISORS FOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HIGH
MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR EYE MELGAR I
AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER EITHER ATTORNEYS AND THE MOTION
IS ADOPTED AS PASSED. ALL RIGHT.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER YOU MAY ASK YOUR QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT AND THANK YOU MAYOR.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. >> I AM INVOKING THIS RARELY
USED BOARD PRIVILEGE BECAUSE OVER THE WEEKEND AS YOU ALL
KNOW THE PRESIDENT EIGHT WAS REPORTED AS DOUBLING DOWN ON
HIS COMMITMENT TO SEND THE NATIONAL GUARD TO SAN
FRANCISCO. HE HAS DEPLOYED FEDERAL FORCES
US AND THE NATIONAL GUARD TO CITIES LIKE CHICAGO, LOS
ANGELES AND PORTLAND. HIS COMMENTS ABOUT OUR CITY
SHOULD NOT BE TAKEN LIGHTLY AND IN THE MISSION WE'VE BEEN
BRACING FOR THIS MOMENT THE MOMENT THAT PEOPLE STOP GOING
TO WORK WHEN ANYONE BLACK OR BROWN CAN'T FREELY WALK OUTSIDE
WITHOUT THE FEAR OF TRUMP'S FEDERAL AGENTS RACIALLY
PROFILING AND ARRESTING THEM THE MOMENT WHEN PARENTS STOP
SENDING THEIR KIDS TO SCHOOL BECOME TOO AFRAID TO GO GET
GROCERIES OR GO TO THE DOCTOR. WHAT WE'VE BEEN PREPARING FOR
IN THE MISSION IS ESSENTIALLY A SHUTDOWN THE LIKES OF WHICH WE
HAVEN'T SEEN SINCE COVID. AND COLLEAGUES, THIS SCENARIO
HAS BECOME INCREASINGLY AND TERRIFYINGLY MORE REAL FOR
THOUSANDS OF OUR CONSTITUENTS OVER THE PAST SIX DAYS AS A
SANCTUARY CITY I BELIEVE SAN FRANCISCANS ARE OWED A
STATEMENT FROM OUR MAYOR ON THE RECORD ABOUT HOW THE MAYOR'S
ADMINISTRATION IS PREPARING TO DEFEND THEIR CIVIL LIBERTIES
AND RIGHTS. AND SO WITH THAT MAYOR, I WOULD
LIKE TO ASK WHAT IS YOUR ADMINISTRATION DOING IN THE
COMING DAYS AND WEEKS? MORE SPECIFICALLY, WHAT
DIRECTION HAVE YOU GIVEN TO RELEVANT GOVERNMENTAL UNITS
AND DEPARTMENTS IN THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY TO PREPARE OUR CITY AND PROTECTING THE CIVIL
LIBERTIES AND RIGHTS OF OUR RESIDENTS AND ESPECIALLY
IMMIGRANTS AND PEOPLE OF COLOR? IN THE EVENT THAT DONALD TRUMP
SENDS MILITARIZED FEDERAL FORCES INCLUDING POTENTIALLY
THE NATIONAL GUARD TO SAN FRANCISCO, I APPRECIATE IT.
>> SUPERVISOR AS EVERYONE IN THIS ROOM KNOWS WE'VE BEEN
CONSTANTLY MONITORING THE POSSIBILITY OF FEDERAL
INTERVENTION. REALLY SINCE THE DAY I TOOK
OFFICE SO THAT WE CAN BE PREPARED TO RESPOND TO AND KEEP
SAN FRANCISCO SAFE UNDER ANY SCENARIO.
I HAVE SAID THIS FROM DAY ONE KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO SAFE IS
MY NUMBER ONE PRIORITY. WE'VE BEEN CONVENING ACROSS
DEPARTMENTAL POLICY GROUP OF PUBLIC SAFETY LEADERS
REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AND OTHER
AFFECTED DEPARTMENT HEADS TO CONTINUE COORDINATING OUR LOCAL
RESPONSE TO POTENTIAL FEDERAL ACTIONS.
THIS POLICY GROUP IS MEETING REGULARLY TO ENSURE OUR
OPERATIONAL STRATEGIC PLANS REMAIN CURRENT AND EFFECTIVE
AND WE JUST ENDED ONE ABOUT AN HOUR AGO.
THE CITY ATTORNEY YESTERDAY FILED A BRIEF IN THE U.S.
SUPREME COURT THEIR FOURTH BRIEF BRIEF ON THIS ISSUE
MAKING IT CLEAR THAT LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT IS BEST POSITIONED
TO KEEP OUR COMMUNITIES SAFE AND THAT THEY ARE DOING IT
WELL. AS YOU KNOW, S.F. PD HAS A LONG
STANDING GENERAL ORDER WHICH INTERIM CHIEF YEP REAFFIRMED
RECENTLY IN THE DEPARTMENT'S NOTICE TO OFFICERS THAT GOVERNS
ENGAGEMENT WITH FEDERAL AUTHORITIES AND ENSURES PD
OFFICERS HAVE CLEAR GUIDANCE. THAT POLICY PROHIBITS S.F. PD
FROM PARTICIPATING IN FEDERAL CIVIL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
IT IS NOT THE ROLE OF LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT TO ASSIST WITH
MILITARY OPERATIONS ON OUR STREETS.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS HAD POLICIES LIKE THIS IN PLACE FOR DECADES
. THEY HELP FOSTER TRUST BETWEEN
LAW ENFORCEMENT AND COMMUNITIES AND THAT HELPS KEEP OUR
COMMUNITY SAFE. AS I HAVE ALWAYS SAID AND WILL
REPEAT AGAIN TODAY, I AM FULLY COMMITTED TO UPHOLDING THOSE
POLICIES. MY ADMINISTRATION IS ALSO
IN REGULAR COMMUNICATION WITH COMMUNITY AND IMMIGRANT LEADERS
TO STAY INFORMED AND RESPONSIVE TO CONDITIONS ON THE GROUND
AND TO OFFER APPROPRIATE RESOURCES.
OF COURSE THAT HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE CASE BUT IT IS PARTICULARLY
IMPORTANT NOW AND I CONTINUE TO DO THAT.
I MAY SAY ONE MORE TIME SO EVERYBODY CAN HEAR THIS.
AS I HAVE SAID, MY TOP PRIORITY IS KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO SAFE
AND I WILL CONTINUE WORKING WITH THIS BOARD HOWEVER I CAN
TO DELIVER ON THAT COMMITMENT TO THE CITY AND TO THE PEOPLE
OF OUR GREAT CITY. I APPRECIATE THE QUESTION.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
>> THIS CONCLUDES THE DISTRICT NINE TOPIC DISCUSSION.
>> THANK YOU FOR JOINING US TODAY.
>> ALL RIGHT. THESE MATTERS HAVE BEEN
DISCUSSED AND WILL BE FILED AFTER GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
AND MADAM CLERK THAT TAKES US BACK TO COMMUNICATIONS.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. I WENT DIRECTLY TO CONSENT.
MY APOLOGIES. >> THANK YOU ALL FOR JOINING
THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER. I WANT TO SAY THAT YOU ARE
NOTICING THAT WE ARE MISSING A MEMBER OF THE BOARD.
AS YOU ALL MAY KNOW THERE IS A VACANCY IN THE DISTRICT FOR
OFFICE AS SOON AS THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE MAKES THE
APPOINTMENT THAT SEAT WILL BE FILLED.
UNTIL THEN THE VOTE THRESHOLD WILL REMAIN SIX VOTES FOR
SUBSTANTIVE VOTES. >> UNLESS AS YOU SAW EARLIER,
THE ORDINANCE REQUIRES A HIGHER VOTE IN WHICH CASE THE VOTE
THRESHOLD WOULD BE HIGHER. >> OF THE ENTIRE MEMBERSHIP OF
THE BOARD. THAT HOUSEKEEPING BIT.
I WANTED TO ALSO THEN IF YOU HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO COME TO
THIS CHAMBER ON A REGULAR BASIS THANK YOU FOR ATTENDING.
OTHERWISE YOU CAN CATCH THE PROCEEDING ON S.F. GO TV'S
CHANNEL 26 AND PROVIDE YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING BY
SENDING EITHER AN EMAIL TO S.F. GOV TO A BOX AT S.F. GOVERNMENT
ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. THE ROOM 244 CITY HALL.
SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 94102. IF YOU NEED A REASONABLE
ACCOMMODATION OR YOU NEED LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE PLEASE
CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO DAYS IN ADVANCE BY
CALLING (415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU TO THE MEMBERS.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO THE APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. WE HAVE APPROVAL OF THE
SEPTEMBER 9TH 2025 AND SEPTEMBER 16TH 2025 BOARD
MEETING MINUTES. >> COLLEAGUES, CAN I HAVE A
MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES MOVED BY WALTON?
CAN I HAVE A SECOND SECONDED BY CHEN.
>> AND MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE
MINUTES AS APPROVED. SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR I THERE ARE TEN EYES.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER
PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED. >> AND NOW MADAM CLERK I THINK
WE'VE CAUGHT UP TO YOU. LET'S GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA.
PLEASE CALL ITEMS TWO THROUGH 16 ITEMS TWO THROUGH 16 ARE ON
CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS A MEMBER MAY ASK FOR AN ITEM TO
BE CONSIDERED SEPARATELY. >> THESE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS
TWO THROUGH 16 SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
HI RANDLEMAN I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR
SAUDER SADR EITHER ARE ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION
THESE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND FINALLY
PASSED AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL
ITEM 17 ITEM 17 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUILDING
AND PLANNING CODES TO COMPLY WITH CALIFORNIA GOVERNMENT CODE
SECTION 66007 BY POSTPONING THE COLLECTION OF DEVELOPMENT
IMPACT FEES FOR DESIGNATED RESIDENTIAL DEVELOPMENT
PROJECTS TO THE DATE OF FIRST CERTIFICATE OF OCCUPANCY OR
FIRST TEMPORARY CERTIFICATE OF OCCUPANCY WHICHEVER OCCURS
FIRST AND TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON MY
APOLOGIES PRESIDENT MELMAN NOT FOR THIS ITEM.
>> OKAY. MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL ON 17 ON ITEM 17. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT MANDEL MAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
THERE ARE NINE EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR FIELDER VOTING
NO AND THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED AND I THINK WE'RE GOING
TO COME BACK TO 8 TO 18 AND 19 LATER.
WILL LET'S GO TO OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER YES THE 230
SPECIAL ORDER IS THE TIME TO CELEBRATE RESIDENTS OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE AND WE WILL START WITH
DISTRICT THREE. >> SUPERVISOR ORDER SORTER
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MANDOLIN COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM HONORED
TO RECOGNIZE RICH MANGANO OF THE DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO
PARTNERSHIP FOR HIS HEROIC LIFE SAVING ACTION IN THIS VERY
BUILDING TWO WEEKS AGO. RICH, CAN YOU COME PLEASE JOIN
US AT THE PODIUM? >> IT WAS AT THE OCTOBER 6TH
ART COMMISSION HEARING UPSTAIRS AND ROOM 416 WHERE A PUBLIC
COMMENT OR COLLAPSED AS HE WAS RETURNING TO HIS SEAT FROM THE
PODIUM ATTENDEES RUSHED OVER TO HIM AND SEEING THAT HE WAS
UNRESPONSIVE PLEADED TO THE ROOM FOR HELP.
>> MOMENTS LIKE THESE REQUIRE QUICK ACTION TO PREVENT SERIOUS
HEALTH IMPACTS AND POSSIBLE LOSS OF LIFE.
FORTUNATELY RICH WHO WAS ALSO ATTENDING THAT HEARING,
ANSWERED THE CALL. RICH PERFORMED CPR.
HE PROVIDED EMERGENCY ASSISTANCE UNTIL THE SHERIFF'S
DEPUTIES AND PARAMEDICS ARRIVED IN ROOM 416.
>> HE DEMONSTRATED COURAGE, SELFLESSNESS AND CARE FOR AN
ABSOLUTE STRANGER THAT DAY. WE ARE GRATEFUL TO LEARN THAT
THE PUBLIC COMMENTER IS RECOVERING WELL FROM THE HEALTH
INCIDENT AND IN FACT I BELIEVE THE TWO OF YOU HAD THE CHANCE
TO BE REUNITED IN THE HOSPITAL ROOM RECENTLY AS HE IS
RECOVERING AND RECOVERING WELL MANY OF YOU KNOW THAT IMMEDIATE
CPR CAN DOUBLE OR TRIPLE THE CHANCE OF A PERSON'S SURVIVAL.
IT IS REPORTED THAT ONLY ABOUT 40% OF PEOPLE GET THE HELP THEY
NEED FROM BYSTANDERS BEFORE FIRST RESPONDERS ARRIVE.
AND WE WERE VERY LUCKY ON THAT DAY IN OCTOBER TO HAVE RICH
THERE TO ANSWER THE CALL RICH JUMPING INTO ACTION PROBABLY
DOESN'T COME AS A SURPRISE TO ANYONE WHO KNOWS HIM.
HE HAS A LONG HISTORY OF SERVING OTHERS.
HE SERVED FOR NEARLY 20 YEARS AS A POLICE OFFICER IN SAN JOSE
AND CURRENTLY HE'S THE VICE PRESIDENT OF OPERATIONS FOR THE
DOWNTOWN NSSF PARTNERSHIP WHERE HE MANAGES THE CLEAN AND SAFE
PROGRAMS AND HE'S DONE A TREMENDOUS JOB AND HAS BEEN A
BIG PART OF OUR DOWNTOWN RECOVERY.
HE AMPLIFIES WHAT IT MEANS TO BE AN EVERYDAY HERO AND HIS
ACTIONS REMIND US TO BE GENEROUS TOWARD STRANGERS TO
HELP WHEN HELP IS NEEDED AND ALWAYS BE PREPARED.
SO ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD RICH, WE WANT TO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
BRAVE LIFESAVING ACTIONS AND WE ALSO WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALL
OF YOUR WORK DOWNTOWN AND IN ALL YOUR SERVICE TO OUR CITY.
SO PLEASE JOIN ME IN WELCOMING RICH TO NOW SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SOUDER FOR THIS HONOR AND YOUR TEAM.
I AM BOTH HONORED AND HUMBLED TO BE RECOGNIZED BY YOU AND THE
BOARD. NO ONE CAN EVER PLAN TO OR
EXPECT TO BE IN A SITUATION LIKE I WAS ON OCTOBER 6TH
AND ALL I KEPT THINKING ABOUT DURING THAT TIME WAS DOING
EVERYTHING THAT I POSSIBLY COULD TO KEEP THAT MAN ALIVE.
I HAD NEVER MET THE GENTLEMAN BEFORE THAT DAY AND MY ONLY
RECOLLECTION OF HIM UP UNTIL A FEW DAYS AGO WAS HIS PHYSICAL
STATE WHEN I BEGAN DOING CPR I HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO MEET HIM
AND HIS FIRST NAME IS CARL. FIVE DAYS AFTER THE INCIDENT
IN HIS HOSPITAL ROOM I HERE IN THE CITY AND WHEN I WALKED
INTO THE ROOM SEEING HIM SITTING UP IN A CHAIR SMILING
THEN CRYING BROUGHT THIS WHOLE EVENT TRULY INTO PERSPECTIVE
AND HE ASKED ME ONLY ONE QUESTION WHAT'S IT LIKE TO SAVE
SOMEBODY'S LIFE? >> I NEVER REALLY THOUGHT OF IT
AND TRULY COULDN'T DESCRIBE THE FEELING I TOLD HIM I HONESTLY
DON'T KNOW HOW TO DESCRIBE IT. I'M JUST GLAD THAT I WAS ABLE
TO BE THERE FOR HIM WHEN HE NEEDED SOMEONE AND THAT I HOPE
THAT IF EVER THAT SITUATION WERE TO FALL ON ME OR ONE OF MY
LOVED ONES SOMEONE WOULD JUMP IN AS WELL.
SO AGAIN, THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU TO THE BOARD.
I'M A NATIVE SAN FRANCISCO AND BORN AND RAISED VERY PROUD
OF THIS CITY AND EVERYTHING THAT IT'S BECOMING.
SO THANK YOU AGAIN FOR THE HONOR
. >> NEXT UP DISTRICT TEN
SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADAM MIN, IF I COULD
GET YOU NECK AND BACK TO COME UP TO THE PODIUM.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM PROUD TO RECOGNIZE SOMEONE WHOSE
DEDICATION TO HER COMMUNITY, HER NEIGHBORS AND TO THE CITY
OF SAN FRANCISCO HAS TRULY STOOD THE TEST OF TIME.
DO BECKON BACK. >> FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES
JUDE HAS POURED HER ENERGY, EXPERTISE AND HEART INTO
NONPROFIT AND COMMUNITY WORK. HER CAREER HAS BRIDGE BOTH THE
CORPORATE AND NONPROFIT WORLDS BUT HER PASSION HAS ALWAYS BEEN
ROOTED RIGHT HERE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS AND PUBLIC SPACES
THAT BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER. >> IN 2015, JUDE TOOK ON A
MAJOR CHALLENGE WITH THE FRIENDS OF JACKSON PARK HELPING
TO CRAFT A VISION FOR THE PARK'S RENOVATION.
NAVIGATING THE MAZE OF CITY AGENCIES AND LEADING THE CHARGE
TO FUNDRAISE AND BRING THAT VISION TO LIFE HER LEADERSHIP,
PERSEVERANCE AND COMMITMENT HAVE BEEN INSTRUMENTAL
IN MOVING THIS PROJECT FORWARD .
AND SHE'S DONE IT ALL WITH A SENSE OF HUMOR DETERMINED
PASSION AND THE RIGHT AMOUNT OF PERSISTENCE.
>> JUDE AND HER HUSBAND DAVE RAISED THREE CHILDREN IN PATROL
HILL WHERE JACKSON PARK BECAME AN EXTENSION OF THEIR BACKYARD.
A DAILY DESTINATION FILLED WITH MEMORIES AND COMMUNITY.
>> YEARS AGO, DREW WORKED WITH NEIGHBORS AND THE CITY TO
REPLACE THE OLD CARCINOGENIC PLAYGROUND EQUIPMENT WITH WHAT
STANDS THERE TODAY PROVED THAT WHEN SHE SETS HER MINDS TO
SOMETHING CHANGE HAPPENS. AND HERE WE ARE AGAIN AS SHE
CONTINUES TO FIGHT FOR JACKSON PARK TO BE BROUGHT INTO THE
21ST CENTURY. SHE IS TIRELESS.
SHE IS PASSIONATE AND SHE IS ABSOLUTELY RELENTLESS.
>> AND THE BEST POSSIBLE WAY WE HONOR JUDE NOT JUST FOR WHAT
SHE'S DONE BUT FOR WHAT SHE CONTINUES TO DO FOR
AND COMMUNITY. FOR HER UNWAVERING COMMITMENT
TO COMMUNITY. FOR HER LOVE OF THIS CITY
AND FOR REMINDING US ALL THAT GREAT THINGS HAPPEN WHEN
NEIGHBORS CARE DEEPLY ENOUGH TO ACT.
>> IF THERE WAS AN IVY LEAGUE COURSE AND IN FACT AN EFFECTIVE
PERSISTENCE YOU WOULD BE THE PROFESSOR.
>> CONGRATULATIONS, JUDE AND THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE AND SPIRIT.
>> THE FLOOR IS YOURS. WELL, GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
>> I HAVE A LOT OF THANK YOU'S FIRST AND FOREMOST TO
SUPERVISOR WALTON. THANK YOU FOR HONORING ME TODAY
AND GIVING ME MY FLOWERS AND FOR YOUR UNDYING SUPPORT OF
THE JACKSON PARK RENOVATION PROJECT.
>> YEAH. AND SPEAKING OF WHICH, HUGE
SHOUT OUT TO MY FAMILY DAVE LUCAS AND JACKSON WHO ARE HERE
TODAY. JULIA IS WATCHING FROM NEW YORK
368 CLUB. >> I LOVE YOU SO THANK YOU.
>> AND NOW I'D LIKE TO ASK ALL THE FRIENDS OF JACKSON PARK TO
STAND UP WHICH SHOULD BE EVERYBODY IN THE ROOM.
>> I'D JUST SAY BECAUSE EVERYBODY LOVES JACKSON FOR
OVER A DECADE THIS COMMUNITY OF JACKSON PARK SUPPORTERS HAS
WORKED WITH OUR PARTNERS REC PARK TO CRAFT OUR PARK
RENOVATION PROJECT THAT WOULD ADDRESS THE GROWING NEEDS OF
GREEN AND OPEN SPACE IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD ADA GUIDELINES
WHICH WE DON'T CURRENTLY MEET AND TO RESTORE AND RENOVATE OUR
HISTORIC FROM 1912 CLUBHOUSE. >> ANYBODY WHO'S BEEN TO
JACKSON AND I'M SURE ALL OF YOU HAVE NO WE NEED SOME HELP HERE
ON OUR BELOVED PARK. >> THIS COMMUNITY HAS ATTENDED
OVER 12 COMMUNITY MEETINGS, TEN STAKEHOLDER MEETINGS, COUNTLESS
COFFEES AND OTHER NEIGHBORHOOD ORGANIZATION MEETINGS ALL TO
SUPPORT THE DESIGN WHICH WAS COMMUNITY DRIVEN AND TO
FUNDRAISE FOR THIS PARK RENOVATION PROJECT.
WE HAVE OUR PROJECT HAS RECEIVED SECRET CLEARANCE.
>> IT WAS A IT GOT UNANIMOUS APPROVAL FROM BOTH THE REC PARK
COMMISSION AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS OVER TWO AND A HALF
YEARS AGO. >> AND WE'VE RAISED A LITTLE
OVER 32 MILLION. >> LET ME REPEAT THAT NUMBER 30
2 MILLION AND THEN THAT'S BOTH IN PLEDGED AND DONATED PUBLIC
AND PRIVATE FUNDS FOR THIS PROJECT WHICH IS A LITTLE OVER
70 5% OF WHAT'S NEEDED ACCORDING TO THE CITY.
>> SO NOW IS THE TIME TO COMPLETE THIS PROJECT.
JACKSON NEEDS TO JUMP UP ON THE LIST OF PRIORITIES AND GET THE
RENOVATION PROJECT THAT WE NEED AND DESERVE.
SO AS I TOLD MAYOR LARRY SUPERVISOR WALTON, GENERAL
MANAGER GINSBERG AND ANYBODY ELSE WHO WOULD LISTEN TO ME, I
AM ASKING TODAY TAKING THIS OPPORTUNITY TO HELP US FUND OUR
GAP FROM THIS BOARD LET'S FIND THAT MONEY.
I PROMISE YOU I WILL STOP BUGGING YOU AND ANY OF ALL OF
YOU ONCE IT'S DONE. >> BUT NOT UNTIL IT'S DONE.
>> SO LET'S WORK TOGETHER AND LET'S BUILD THIS PARK.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR HELP TO WE'RE GOING TO GIVE JUDE'S
FRIENDS A CHANCE TO GET OUT OF THE CHAMBER BEFORE WE GO TO OUR
DISTRICT 11 HONOREE
. >> ALL RIGHT, SUPERVISOR CHEN,
YOU HAVE AN HONOREE? >> YEAH.
THANK YOU. PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
GOOD AFTERNOON, COLLEAGUES AND EVERYONE TODAY I'M SO PROUD
TO HONOR PAUL SAMPSON, A PASSIONATE ADVOCATES FOR HOME
CARE WORKERS, A DEDICATED COMMUNITY MEMBER AND AN
INSPIRATIONAL INSPIRATIONAL LEADER IN BOTH THE LABOR
MOVEMENT AND THE CHINESE-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
>> MR. POEM BEGAN HIS JOURNEY AS A TEACHER IN CHINA BEFORE
IMMIGRATING TO THE UNITED STATES.
>> HE IS AN INSPIRATION. >> HE IS ALSO INSPIRING EXAMPLE
OF MANY WHO OVERCAME LANGUAGE AND CULTURAL BARRIERS TO FULLY
ENGAGE IN OUR COMMUNITY LEADING WITH HEART DEDICATION AND A
TRUE SPIRIT OF SERVICE. >> AFTER IMMIGRATING TO SAN
FRANCISCO IN TWO THOUSAND, MR. BEGAN WORKING WITH THE IN-HOME
SUPPORTIVE SERVICES TO CARE FOR HIS OWN FAMILY.
THAT SAME YEAR HE JOINED SEIU U H W UNITED HEALTH CARE WORKERS
WEST. >> STANDING IN UNITY FOR
WORKERS RIGHTS AND SOCIAL JUSTICE.
IN 2011 HE WAS ELECTED AS AN EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF SEIU UAW
AND IN 2017 APPOINTED AS A VICE PRESIDENT OF SEIU LOCAL 2015
BAY AREA CHAPTERS. >> THIS IS TRULY A TESTAMENT TO
HIS DETERMINATION AND ORGANIZING SKILLS
AND LEADERSHIP. THANKS TO YOUR TIRELESS EFFORTS
MR. AND YOUR LOCAL 2015 NEGOTIATION TEAM.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HOMECARE WORKERS NOW ENJOY ONE OF THE
STRONGEST UNIONS CONTRACTS IN THE BAY AREA AND IT'S A
MODEL FOR OTHERS NATIONWIDE. >> WHY EVEN NOW YOU ARE
IN RETIREMENT. YOU CONTINUE TO SERVE.
>> YOU MOBILIZE UNION MEMBERS, MENTORS, YOUNG LEADERS SUPPORT
EDUCATION AND CULTURAL PROGRAMS AND ADVICE COMMUNITY EVENTS
LIKE YOUR NEIGHBORHOOD RICHMOND NUNA NEW STREET FAIR TOGETHER
WHERE LEADERS IN THE COMMUNITY LIKE SALLY CHANG, SAM ZHOU
GOLDMAN, HONG YANG KAI LAN EVA JOLLY AND HONG HU TONY CHEN.
>> MR. PUTIN HAS CONTINUE TO HELP LEAD A POWERFUL COALITION
OF RETIRE LEADERS CONTINUE TO INSPIRE AND SUPPORT AND PASS ON
THEIR ORGANIZING WISDOM TO FUTURE GENERATION IN SAN
FRANCISCO. AND I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO SAY IF
YOU WERE IN CHINESE PARTIZAN GOVERNMENT THAT TIE YOU WERE
ONLY SEEKING PARTIZAN TOLLING. >> HI JOAN GOT YANG GOUT.
HI SUN CANCER. >> HIRED YOU.
THANK YOU MAN DON'T MAKE OUT SEE HOW COULD HAVE COOKED ALL
YOU EAT UNTIL MY MAGGOTS ROUTINE TICKET TALLY UP SIX
FOOTNOTE YOU KNOW HOW COME WE GET ONE YAPPING YONG HUNG
HOUSE OUR LOKONGA CONNECT ON MY GYM YOU GOT LITTLE DIYALA YI
AND I YOU SOME FOOTBALL TOTAL MONTH I WOULD DON'T LIKE THOUGH
SAY I QUIT KONGOLO COME ON GUY ARE $1 GAMBIA UP WHEN SONG HEY
TITLE HIM A WHOLE TO BE TORTURE YOU HAVE $20 I POINT HIGH YEAH
THE WHOLE DADDY I PUT MAMA TILL MY PUDDING SONG I HATE HOT OKAY
YOUNG LADY LADY YOU NEED SONG SAY WE DON'T SAY I QUOTE FROM
HAMPTON SANG YEAH MY LADY GOT LIKE ITEMIZING TUNE THAT PUTS
NANCY HOW YOU TUNE SOMEHOW HE SINGS OUT MORE THEY COME YEAH
SEQUOIA ELEPHANT GUM DON'T TELL MY KING HOW LIKE POINTS OUT
THEY HANG ALL DAY SAY I AT ONE NOON HANG ORDER IT'S A STICKING
POINT GUY BANIA BUDDY LIKE YOU ALI HOW YOU GOT AND FIRST
SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT BENJAMIN AND FIRST
I'M GOING TO SAY THAT IN ENGLISH AND TO I WANT TO BE
ABLE TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO MR. IN CHINESE AS WELL.
>> I'M NOT GOING TO I CONCUR WITH SO MUCH OF A OF THE
SENTIMENTS THAT SUPERVISOR CHEN HAS ALREADY EXPRESSED TOWARD
MR. PUTIN. >> BUT MR. PUTIN HAS BEEN
REALLY A LONG TIME DISTRICT ONE RESIDENCE AT THE SITES ON BY A
GIRL IN GARY AND NOW BUT REALLY OFFICIALLY IN DISTRICT TWO
LUCKY SUPERVISOR CHERYL AND BUT MR. PUTIN HAS ALWAYS BEEN A
COMMUNITY LEADER TAKING CARE OF HIS NEIGHBORS, THE PEOPLE THAT
LIVE IN THAT VERY SAME BUILDING AND MAKING SURE THAT THEY
UNDERSTAND THEIR RIGHTS, WHATEVER THAT IS HAPPENING
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD. SO FOR THAT I'M JUST SO
GRATEFUL TO MR. PUTIN
. OH, AND I WILL JUST SAY I THINK
THAT THE ENTIRE BOARD IS GRATEFUL FOR THIS COMMENDATION.
SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR OFFERING IT AND NOW YOU CAN
SPEAK WITH ALL THE TRANSLATIONS YOU TIMES YOU
EARN TODAY I AM DEEPLY HONORED TO ACCEPT THIS CERTIFICATE OF
HONOR AND TO BE RECOGNIZED HERE BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
IN THIS GRAND CHAMBER. >> THIS RECOGNITION AFFIRMS MY
OVER 20 YEARS OF SOCIAL ACTIVISM AND COMMUNITY SERVICE
. IT ALSO ACKNOWLEDGES THOSE WHO
HAVE COLLABORATED WITH ME SUPPORT IT ME AND STAND BY MY
SIDE TODAY. HERE WITH ME IS MY WIFE DOLLY
PENG. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR
UNWAVERING SUPPORT AND YOUR UNDERSTANDING.
>> I AM ALSO VERY GRATEFUL TO MANAGER YANG WAILING OF THE
COMES ON CHINESE NEW COMERS ASSOCIATION AND MUTUAL AID
ASSOCIATION WHO HELPED ME GAIN A FOOTHOLD IN AMERICA AFTER
IMMIGRATING. >> I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK
FORMER EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE SEIU UAW SAN FRANCISCO
CHAPTER SALLY JEWSON GOMAN AND MEMBER LIN FOR THANK YOU TO
THE CHAIRPERSON WANG FROM MY HOMETOWN ASSOCIATION
AND CHAIRPERSON WANG YI HONG FROM THE WHAT RESIDENTS
ASSOCIATION AND ALSO THANK YOU SO MUCH TO SEVERAL SENIOR
CLASSMATES OUT IN THE RICHMOND WHO HELPED AND STUDIED
ALONGSIDE WITH ME DIGITAL EDUCATION AND I THANK YOU AGAIN
TO ALL OF THE COMMUNITY AND TO THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR YOUR ENCOURAGEMENT.
I HOPE THAT MORE IMMIGRANTS AND IMMIGRANT ELDERS WILL
ACTIVELY PARTICIPATE IN ADVOCATING FOR CIVIL RIGHTS
LEGISLATION AND BUDGETS TO GIVE ALL
CHURCH TO AT AND NOW DISTRICT ONE.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDELMAN COLLEAGUES
TODAY I'M HONORING ONE OF THE RICH RICHMOND'S MOST CHERISHED
RESOURCES THE INTERNET ARCHIVE. WE ARE JUST SO GRATEFUL THAT
FOR THEIR ACCOMPLISHMENTS NOT JUST FOR SAN FRANCISCO FOR THE
RICHMOND BUT REALLY I WOULD SAY FOR THE ENTIRE NATION.
AND TODAY TOMORROW IS INTERNET ARCHIVE, ITS 26TH ANNIVERSARY
THAT IS 26 YEARS 29 OH 29 I WAS LIKE LOOKING ROBIN AND I WAS
LIKE I THINK THAT WE KNOW THAT WE KNEW THAT 29 YEARS OF
PROTECTING OUR FIRST AMENDMENT RIGHTS AND CREATING EQUITABLE
ACCESS TO INFORMATION IN TODAY'S WORLD COLLEAGUES
THIS ACCESS IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVER.
WE KNOW THAT WHEN OUR FIRST AMENDMENT RIGHTS IS UNDER
ATTACK, WHEN OUR PUBLIC LIBRARIES ARE UNDER ATTACK THIS
WHEN WE TALK ABOUT INTERNET ARCHIVE'S WORK, WHEN WE TALK
ABOUT ALL THAT THIS ORGANIZATION HAS DONE IS MORE
CRITICAL THAN EVER WHEN WE'RE SEEING BOOKS BANNED AND PEOPLE
SILENCED THE INTERNET ARCHIVE STANDS UP AND ENSURE FREE
ACCESS TO VITAL INFORMATION. AND UNDER THE LEADERSHIP OF
BREWSTER KAEL WHEN I WHO I CALL CALLED THE BRAIN BEHIND
INTERNET ARCHIVE THIS INSTITUTION ALSO NOW
CELEBRATING AN ENORMOUS ACCOMPLISHMENT OF THEIR 1
TRILLION WEB PAGES ARCHIVED THIS IS AN INCREDIBLE A
ACHIEVEMENT AND A TESTAMENT TO AND TESTAMENT TO THEIR
UNWAVERING COMMITMENT. IN ADDITION TO THE WEB PAGES,
THE INTERNET ARCHIVE HAS PRESERVED 49 MILLION BOOKS
AND TEXT 13 MILLION AUDIO RECORDINGS 10 MILLION VIDEOS, 5
MILLION IMAGES AND 1 MILLION SOFTWARE PROGRAMS.
AND WE KNOW THAT AS I HAVE LEARNED TODAY, OUR MR.
LIBRARIAN MICHAEL LAMBERT MENTIONED THAT WHEN INTERNET
ARCHIVE STARTED IN 1996 WAS THE VERY SAME YEAR THAT OUR MAIN
LIBRARY TO FLASH AT LIBRARY ACROSS THE STREETS BEGAN.
>> AND SINCE THEN THERE'S AN ONGOING PARTNERSHIP.
THANKS TO BREWSTER IN 2008 SUPPORTING OUR PUBLIC LIBRARY
AND BEING ABLE TO AGAIN HAVE ACCESS TO OUR INFORMATION
AND TO OUR LIBRARY ONLINE. >> IT JUST WE'RE JUST
TREMENDOUSLY GRATEFUL FOR INTERNET ARCHIVE AND THAT WHAT
YOU WANT THEM TO KNOW THAT THIS FOR SUPERVISORS THE CITY
AND COUNTY SAN FRANCISCO WILL ALWAYS BE IN SOLIDARITY WITH
INTERNET ARCHIVE IN A FIGHT FOR FIRST AMENDMENT RIGHT AND THE
FIGHT FOR PUBLIC INFORMATION AND ACCESS TO FREE INFORMATION.
>> AND SO WITH THAT TODAY I'M VERY HAPPY THAT WE ARE GOING TO
HONOR INTERNET ARCHIVE DAY CELEBRATING AND DECLARING
OCTOBER 22ND THAT INTERNET INTERNET ARCHIVE DAY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THANK YOU CONNIE CHAN PORTER TO
FRASERS THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR MAKING THIS THE WELCOME HOME OF
THE INTERNET ARCHIVE. WE WERE BORN AND BRED IN AND
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I'D SAY THE INTERNET ARCHIVE AS WELL AS
A LOT OF OTHER NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS AND HIGH TECH
NONPROFITS ARE REALLY THIS IS A NATURAL HOME FOR IT BECAUSE OF
THE SUPPORTIVE NATURE. SO LIKE WIKIPEDIA, LIKE THE
ELECTRONIC FRONTIER FOUNDATION ,THE INTERNET ARCHIVE IS PART
OF THE BEDROCK FABRIC OF THE INTERNET AND IS VERY MUCH A SAN
FRANCISCO STYLE PROJECT AND MORE THAN JUST A SAN
FRANCISCO BORN AND BRED THROUGH THE EVOLUTION OF THE INTERNET
WHICH HAS ALWAYS BEEN OPEN TO THE RIGHT SAN FRANCISCANS
AND SAN FRANCISCO GOVERNORS GOVERNMENT SUPERVISORS HAVE
ALWAYS BEEN IN SUPPORT. THIS IS A TIME THAT'S EXTREMELY
IMPORTANT AS AS SUPERVISOR CONNIE CHEN JUST SAID, IT'S A
TOUGH TIME FOR LIBRARIES WE'RE GETTING THERE'S CRIMINALIZATION
OF LIBRARIANSHIP NOW THERE'S BOOK BURNINGS.
DEFUNDING IS VERY DIFFICULT LICENSING ENVIRONMENTS THAT ARE
MAKING OUR LIBRARIES HAVE A HARDER AND HARDER TIME DOING
OUR CORE FUNCTIONS AND THE IDEA OF HAVING THIS COMMENDATION IS
FANTASTIC. THE IDEA THAT THERE IS A
INTERNET ARCHIVE DAY TO CELEBRATE 1 TRILLION WEB PAGES
AUTHORED BY OVER A BILLION PEOPLE NOW IN A LIBRARY IN SAN
FRANCISCO IS KIND OF AWESOME. IT REALLY SHOWS THAT PEOPLE
WANT TO SHARE WANT TO HAVE WHAT THEY KNOW AVAILABLE TO THE
WORLD BY THE BILLIONS OF PEOPLE AND THAT WE WERE ABLE TO GO
AND COLLECT THESE RECOGNIZE THE BILLION VOICES THAT IS THE
WORLD WIDE WEB OVER THE LAST 30 YEARS TO GIVE IT A HOME
AND PERMANENCE SHOWS THE SIGNIFICANCE OF THAT WORK.
BUT ALSO WHAT A PLACE LIKE SAN FRANCISCO BRINGS TO BEAR FOR
OUR COMMON WORLD. SO I JUST LIKE TO SAY THANK YOU
VERY MUCH AND WE'RE HONORED THAT THERE IS AN INTERNET
ARCHIVE DAY COMING UP TOMORROW .
>> AND IN THAT NOTE WE'RE GOING TO CLOSE DOWN A STREET
IN RICHMOND AT FUNSTON, LONG PARK, PRESIDIO AND CLEMENT
AND YOUR ALL INVITED IT'S A BIG PARTY TO CELEBRATE 1 TRILLION
WEB PAGE A ONCE IN A GENERATION ACCOMPLISHMENT FAR OUTSTRIPPING
THE LIBRARY OF ALEXANDRIA OR EVEN THE LIBRARY OF CONGRESS
IN SHEER VOLUME. >> LET'S CELEBRATE IN THE
RICHMOND DISTRICT TOMORROW NIGHT.
>> YOU'RE ALL INVITED. THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. AND THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> THANK YOU ALL. >> ALL RIGHT.
I THINK THAT CONCLUDES OUR 230 SPECIAL COMMENDATIONS.
MADAM CLERK. >> LET'S GO BACK TO ITEMS 18
AND 19 IF YOU COULD CALL THEM TOGETHER ITEMS 18 AND 19 ARE
TWO ORDINANCES THAT AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS
CODE ITEM 18 TEMPORARILY EXEMPTS TRANSFERS OF CERTAIN
RENT RESTRICTED AFFORDABLE HOUSING FROM THE REAL PROPERTY
TRANSFER TAX RETROACTIVE TO TRANSFERS ON OR AFTER APRIL
12TH, 2024 AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION ITEM 19
EXCLUDES FROM GROSS RECEIPTS TAX THE GROSS RECEIPTS OF LOW
INCOME HOUSING PARTNERSHIPS RECEIVED FROM THE LEASE OF
RESIDENTIAL REAL ESTATE BEGINNING WITH THE 2026 TAX
YEAR IT SUSPENDS THE BUSINESS REGISTRATION CERTIFICATE
AND FEE REQUIREMENTS OF THOSE PARTNERSHIPS BEGINNING WITH THE
REGISTRATION YEAR COMMENCING APRIL 1ST, 2026 EXEMPTS FROM
CITY EXEMPTS THE CITY FROM THE COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX
RETROACTIVE TO JANUARY 1ST 2025 AND EXEMPTS PERSONS HOLDING
PROPERTY TO BE USED FOR CITY SPONSORED AFFORDABLE HOUSING
PROJECTS FROM THE COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAX RETROACTIVE TO
JANUARY 1ST, 2022 AND REFUNDS COMMERCIAL VACANCY TAXES PAID
BY EXEMPT PERSONS I SHALL STATE FOR ITEM 19 THIS IS
IN ACCORDANCE WITH SECTION 2811 AND OF ARTICLE 28 AND SECTION
20 909 OF ARTICLE 29 OF THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS
CODE. THE PASSAGE OF THIS ORDINANCE
ON FIRST READING IS AN EIGHT VOTE REQUIREMENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK AND SURPRISE WALTON.
YOU DIDN'T HAVE SOMETHING ON ONE OF THESE RIGHT NOW NO
PRESIDENT MADAM AND I WAS JUST GOING TO ASK FOR A ROLL CALL ON
THEM BUT THAT WAS AUTOMATIC BECAUSE THE LAST VOTE GOT IT
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 18
AND 19 SUPERVISORS CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON NO
WALTON NO SUPERVISOR CHEN I CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MENDELSON HI
MIDDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SORTER
SADR I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND TWO NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS
WALTON AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON
FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 ITEM 20
THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE RECREATION
AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND CASH AND OR IN-KIND
GRANTS VALUED AT APPROXIMATELY 500,000 FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
IRISH FAMINE MEMORIAL COMMITTEE FOR THE IRISH FAMINE MEMORIAL
PROJECT PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 20 SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN
CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SUTTER SUTTER I THERE ARE TEN EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 21 ITEM 21 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE GENERAL MANAGER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION TO EXECUTE A FUNDING
AND LICENSE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE COMMISSION AND THE UNIFIED
SCHOOL DISTRICT FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OPERATION
AND MAINTENANCE OF AN ON SITE SOLAR PHOTOVOLTAIC SYSTEM AT
THE MISSION BAY SCHOOL FOR 653,000 AND FOR A 30 YEAR TERM
THROUGH OCTOBER 31ST 2050 FIVE. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 22. ITEM 20 TWO THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE GENERAL
MANAGER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION TO
EXECUTE THE THIRD AMENDMENT TO A CONTRACT FOR POWER SCHEDULING
COORDINATION AND RELATED SUPPORT SERVICES WITH APP SYNC
TO ALLOW FOR THE PROCESSING OF THE CALIFORNIA INDEPENDENT
SYSTEM OPERATOR POWER TRANSMISSION SERVICE CHARGES TO
INCREASE THE CONTRACT BY 365 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL
CONTRACT AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 1.26 BILLION
AND AN ADDITIONAL THREE YEAR TERM EXTENSION FOR A TOTAL TERM
OF MAY 31ST 2022 THROUGH MAY 25TH 2030.
AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS
23 AND 24 TOGETHER ITEMS 23 AND 24 COMPRISE TWO RESOLUTIONS
THAT PERTAIN TO CHILD CARE GRANT AGREEMENTS.
FOR ITEM 23 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY
APPROVE A CONTRACT BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY FOR IMPLEMENT
TATION OF THE CITYWIDE PLAN FOR ELDERLY CARE AND EDUCATION FOR
A THREE YEAR AND SIX MONTH TERM THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2028 FOR
A NEW AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 436 MILLION ITEM 24.
THIS RESOLUTION RETROACTIVELY APPROVES A CONTRACT BETWEEN THE
CITY AND WU YI CHILDREN'S SERVICES FOR THE IMPLEMENTATION
OF THE CITYWIDE PLAN FOR EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION FOR A THREE
YEAR AND SIX MONTH TERM THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST, 2028 AND FOR A
NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 238 MILLION SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 25.
>> ITEM 25 THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE
DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO ENTER INTO A LEASE OF APPROXIMATELY
12,000FT2 OF REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 845 JACKSON STREET
ON THE FOURTH FLOOR WITH CHINESE HOSPITAL ASSOCIATION
FOR AN INITIAL TERM OF THREE YEARS WITH ONE OPTION TO EXTEND
FOR ONE YEAR FOR AN INITIAL ANNUAL BASE RENT OF
APPROXIMATELY 500,000. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
26. ITEM 26 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
APPROVE A FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE LEASE AGREEMENT WITH THE
TRANSBAY JOINT POWERS AUTHORITY FOR CONTINUED MUNI OPERATIONS
AT THE SALESFORCE TRANSIT CENTER LOCATED AT FIRST
AND MISSION STREETS FOR A TERM THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2050 WITH
210 YEAR EXTENSION OPTIONS AND A CURRENT ESTIMATED ANNUAL
OPERATING CHARGE OF APPROXIMATELY 1.2 MILLION.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 27 ITEM 27. >> THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT IS
RETROACTIVE TO APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE GENERAL
MANAGER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION TO
EXECUTE A MEMORANDUM OF AGREEMENT WITH THE CITY OF DALY
CITY FOR FUNDING CONSTRUCTION AND OPERATION OF THE VISTA
GRAND DRAINAGE BASIN IMPROVEMENT PROJECT FOR 35
MILLION WITH A DURATION OF FIVE YEARS AUGUST 4TH, 2025 THROUGH
AUGUST 31ST 2030. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 EIGHT ITEM 28 THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO MODIFY THE GEARY BOULEVARD NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL DISTRICT TO AUTHORIZE OUTDOOR HAND-WASHING,
VACUUMING AND DETAILING OF AUTOMOBILES AS AN ACCESSORY USE
IN CERTAIN AUTOMOTIVE SERVICE STATIONS TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 29 ITEM 29 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ADD THE
COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME JIM MARSHALL WAY ON 16TH STREET
BETWEEN NOYES STREET AND CASTRO STREET IN RECOGNITION OF HIS
CONTRIBUTIONS TO CAPTURING THE CULTURAL AND MUSIC HISTORY OF
SAN FRANCISCO. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 30 THROUGH 45 TOGETHER ITEMS 30
THROUGH 45 OUR 16 RESOLUTIONS THAT INITIATE LANDMARK
DESIGNATIONS UNDER ARTICLE TEN OF THE PLANNING CODE FOR ITEM
30 THIS IS FOR THE FIREHOUSE HOSE COMPANY NUMBER 30 LOCATED
AT 1757 WALLER STREET. ITEM 31 IS FOR MODS LOCATED AT
929 THROUGH 941 COLE STREET. ITEM 32 IS FOR ST MATTHEW'S
CHURCH LOCATED AT 3280 1/16 STREET FOR ITEM 33 THIS IS FOR
THE SAINT NICHOLAS CATHEDRAL LOCATED AT 2005 15TH STREET.
ITEM 34 IS FOR ST PAUL'S CHURCH LOCATED AT 1660 CHURCH STREET.
ITEM 35 IS FOR 102 GUERRERO STREET.
ITEM 36 IS FOR THE BANK OF ITALY.
THE BRANCH BUILDING LOCATED AT 400 THROUGH 410 CASTRO STREET.
ITEM 37 IS FOR BOB ROSS HOUSE AT 40 220TH STREET.
ITEM 38 IS FOR THE CASTRO ROCK STEAM BATHS LOCATED AT 578
THROUGH 582 CASTRO STREET. ITEM 39 IS FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO AIDS FOUNDATION 514 THROUGH 520 CASTRO STREET.
ITEM 40 IS FOR THE FULL MOON COFFEEHOUSE LOCATED AT 4416
18TH STREET. ITEM 41 IS FOR 110 DIAMOND
STREET CHURCH LOCATED AT 100 DIAMOND STREET.
THE RECTORY AT 115 DIAMOND STREET AND THE CONVENT LOCATED
AT 117 DIAMOND STREET AND THE SCHOOL ITEM 42 IS FOR CHARITY
OF THE HISTORIC LOCATION LOCATED AT 220 DANVERS STREET.
ITEM 43 THIS IS FOR 361 SAN JOSE AVENUE FOR ITEM 44 THIS IS
FOR THE CHARTER SCHOOL HOUSE LOCATED AT 1451 MASONIC AVENUE
AND FOR ITEM 45 THIS IS FOR THE ENGINE COMPANY NUMBER 13 AT
1458 VALENCIA STREET. >> ALL RIGHT.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 46.
ITEM 46 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ACCEPT THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S
REPORT THAT ADDS THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING THE CONTROLLERS OFFICE AND DATA S.F. TO THE PREVIOUSLY
DESIGNATIONS AND THAT INCLUDED THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
FIRE DEPARTMENT, THE HEALTH SERVICES ITEM, THE CITY
ATTORNEY, THE TREASURER TAX COLLECTOR AND THE DEPARTMENT OF
TECHNOLOGY AS HEALTH CARE COMPONENTS UNDER THE HEALTH
INSURANCE PORTABILITY AND ACCOUNTABILITY ACT OF 1996
KNOWN AS HIPA PURSUANT TO ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER 22
H. >> AND SAME HOUSE SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 47.
>> ITEM 47 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE THAT AMENDS THE ADMINISTRATE OF
CODE TO CREATE THE UNION STREET ENTERTAINMENT ZONE ON UNION
STREET BETWEEN GOFF AND STEINER STREETS AND ON FILLMORE STREET
BETWEEN UNION AND GREENWICH STREETS AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 48 ITEM 48 THIS RESOLUTION ACCEPTS
THE ANNUAL SURVEILLANCE REPORT FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL
TRANSPORTATION AGENCY UNDER THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTION
19.6. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 49.
>> ITEM 40 NINE THIS MOTION APPOINTS ANKITA MUK PARRA HE
KUMAR TO THE SUNSHINE ORDINANCE TASK FORCE TERM ENDING APRIL
27TH 2027. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 50.
>> ITEM 50 THIS MOTION APPOINTS BENJAMIN TINGLE TO THE CITIZENS
GENERAL OBLIGATION BOND OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE TERM ENDING
NOVEMBER 21ST, 2026. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 51.
>> ITEM 51 THIS MOTION APPOINTS JENNIFER HAND TO THE CHILDREN
YOUTH AND THEIR FAMILIES OVERSIGHT AND ADVISORY
COMMITTEE TERM ENDING JULY 1ST, 2026.
>> SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL IS THE FIRST MEMBER TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS. >> SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE AN IN MEMORIAM AND TWO RESOLUTIONS
TO INTRODUCE. FIRST I WANT TO CELEBRATE THE
LIFE AND LEGACY OF KAREN JEAN PIERCE, A WOMAN WHOSE PRESENCE
BROUGHT LIGHT PURPOSE AND COMPASSION TO EVERYONE WHO
KNEW HER. >> KAREN WAS BORN ON FEBRUARY
4TH, 1947 RIGHT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THE CITY SHE LOVED
SO DEEPLY AND NEVER LEFT. FROM AN EARLY AGE IT WAS CLEAR
SHE HAD BOTH A BRILLIANT MIND AND A GENEROUS HEART.
>> SHE GRADUATED SUMMA LOWRY FROM SAN FRANCISCO STATE
UNIVERSITY AND ONE WENT ON TO EARN HER LAW DEGREE FROM UC
HASTINGS. KAREN'S TRUE CALLING WAS ALWAYS
ABOUT PEOPLE ESPECIALLY CHILDREN FAMILIES
AND COMMUNITIES THAT TOO OFTEN GO FORGOTTEN.
FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS. SHE SERVED AT SAN FRANCISCO
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH WHERE SHE BECAME THE
DEPARTMENT'S FIRST AND ONLY ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE MANAGER.
THAT TITLE ALONE TELLS YOU SOMETHING ABOUT HER SPIRIT
AND SHE DID NOT WAIT FOR PATHS TO BE PAVED.
SHE CREATED THEM THROUGH HER WORK.
SHE FOUGHT FOR CLEAN AIR, SAFER NEIGHBORHOODS, GREATER EQUITY
PARTICULARLY IN BAYVIEW HUNTERS POINT.
SHE LISTENED DEEPLY, SPOKE TRUTH TO POWER AND TURNED
ADVOCACY INTO ACTION. >> THE IMPACT OF HER WORK STILL
RIPPLES THROUGH THIS CITY AND WILL FOR YEARS TO COME.
BEYOND HER PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS, KAREN LIVED WITH
BALANCE AND WITH JOY. SHE LOVED THE GOOD BOOK.
THE CHALLENGE OF A THOUSAND PIECE PUZZLE AND THE SMELL OF
SOMETHING HOMEMADE BAKING IN THE OVEN.
>> SHE ALSO HAD AN ADVENTUROUS SIDE COMPLETING THREE MARATHONS
AFTER THE AGE OF 15 WITH RACES THAT TOOK HER TO BERMUDA,
HAWAII AND EVEN ALASKA. >> THAT SAME DETERMINATION THAT
FUELED HER ADVOCACY CARRIED HER ACROSS FINISH LINES MOST WOULD
NEVER ATTEMPT. THOSE WHO KNEW KAREN DESCRIBED
HER AS STRONG BUT GENTLE. SERIOUS WHEN IT MATTERED BUT
QUICK TO SMILE. DEEPLY COMPASSIONATE YET
UNWAVERING IN HER PRINCIPLES. SHE WAS A LISTENER, A MENTOR, A
FIGHTER FOR WHAT'S RIGHT. >> AND ABOVE ALL, SHE WAS KIND.
HER LIFE REMINDS US THAT CHANGE DOESN'T ALWAYS COME FROM LOUD
VOICES. OUR BIG GESTURES ALTHOUGH SHE
ALWAYS GOT OUR POINT MADE SOMETIMES IT COMES FROM QUIET
STRENGTH, STEADY PERSISTENCE AND A HEART THAT REFUSES TO
GIVE UP ON PEOPLE. >> ALTHOUGH KAREN HAS LEFT THIS
WORLD HER IMPACT ON HER FAMILY, HER COMMUNITY INNER CITY WILL
CONTINUE TO GROW. MAY WE HONOR HER BY LIVING WITH
THAT SAME PURPOSE AND GRACE AND EVERYONE HERE THAT'S HERE
IN SUPPORT OF KAREN. >> COULD YOU JUST STAND SO WE
COULD SEE? THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE TO
HONOR HER COLLEAGUES AND ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION A
RESOLUTION CALLING FOR MOTORIZED SCOOTER ENFORCEMENT
ON SIDEWALKS IN ORDER TO PROTECT PROTEST TRENDS AND KEEP
PEOPLE SAFE. >> OUR SIDEWALKS ARE WHERE
EVERYONE WALKS WHETHER IT'S SENIORS, CHILDREN, FAMILIES,
PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES AND NEIGHBORS MOVING THROUGH
THEIR COMMUNITY. THEY ARE MEANT TO BE SAFE,
PREDICTABLE SPACES FOR PEDESTRIANS NOT SHARE WITH FAST
MOVING ELECTRIC OR GAS POWERED SCOOTERS.
RIDING SCOOTERS ON SIDEWALKS IS NOT ONLY ILLEGAL, IT IS
DANGEROUS AND IT UNDERMINES A SENSE OF SAFETY THAT EVERY
PERSON DESERVES. WALKING IN SAN FRANCISCO UNDER
CALIFORNIA VEHICLE CODE AND SAN FRANCISCO TRANSPORTATION CODE
IT IS ALREADY PROHIBITED TO RIDE SCOOTERS ON SIDEWALKS.
YET WE CONTINUE TO SEE RIDERS TREATING SIDEWALKS LIKE
THOROUGH WAYS OFTEN AT HIGH SPEEDS.
THIS BEHAVIOR PUTS PEDESTRIANS AT SERIOUS RISK AND GOES
AGAINST THE CORE PRINCIPLES OF OUR CITY'S VISION ZERO
COMMITMENT. >> A DISTRICT TEN RESIDENT
RECENTLY WROTE ABOUT HER 84 YEAR OLD FATHER WHO IS UNSTEADY
ON HIS FEET. A SCOOTER DOESN'T EVEN HAVE TO
HIT HIM. THE SHOCK OF ONE ZOOMING BY
COULD CAUSE HIM TO FALL WITH SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES FOR HIS
HEALTH. MANY OF US HAVE FAMILY OR
COMMUNITY MEMBERS IN THE SAME POSITION OUR ELDERS, CHILDREN
AND PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES DESERVE SIDEWALKS THAT FEEL
SAFE AND WALKABLE. NOT STRESSFUL OR FRIGHTENING.
>> WHILE IT'S A FORM TO REGULATE SHARED SCOOTERS, WE
HAVE SEEN A RAPID INCREASE IN PRIVATELY OWNED SCOOTERS.
AND ENFORCEMENT OF THESE VIOLATIONS DEPENDS ON SPEEDY.
THIS RESOLUTION CALLS FOR STRONGER COORDINATION BETWEEN
S.F. MTA AND SPEEDY TO TREAT SIDEWALKS SCOOTER RIDING AS THE
MOVE IN VIOLATION THAT IT IS AND TO PRIORITIZE ENFORCEMENT
AND EDUCATION IN HIGH PEDESTRIAN AREAS SUCH AS
COMMERCIAL CORRIDORS, SENIOR CENTERS AND SCHOOL SCHOOL
ZONES. >> IT ALSO CALLS FOR CLEAR
SIGNAGE REMINDING RIDERS THAT SIDEWALKS ARE FOR WALKING
AND FOR RESIDENTS TO CONTINUE REPORTING VIOLATIONS THROUGH
311 TO HELP GUIDE ENFORCEMENT RESOURCES.
>> EVERYONE RIDERS, DRIVERS AND PEDESTRIANS SHARE
RESPONSIBILITY FOR KEEPING OUR CITY SAFE.
WE CAN SUPPORT NEW FORMS OF MOBILITY BUT NEVER AT THE
EXPENSE OF THOSE WHO WALK. SIDEWALKS BELONG TO PEOPLE WHO
WALK AND THIS MEASURE REAFFIRMS THAT SIMPLE BUT VITAL TRUTH.
>> AND LASTLY, COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
AND SUPPORT FOR WOMEN BASKETBALL PLAYERS REPRESENTED
BY THE WOMEN'S NATIONAL BASKETBALL PLAYERS ASSOCIATION,
INCLUDING THE GOLDEN STATE VALKYRIES WHO HAVE KICKED OFF
THEIR INAUGURAL SEASON THIS YEAR WITH A PLAYOFF RUN.
THIS RESOLUTION CALLS ON THE WNBA TO REACH A FAIR CONTRACT
THAT GIVES PLAYERS BETTER PAY BENEFITS AND WORKING CONDITIONS
THAT KEEP THEM HEALTHY AND SAFE .
>> THE WNBA IS THE FIRST PROFESSIONAL SPORTS UNION FOR
WOMEN. >> THESE PLAYERS ARE NOT ONLY
ATHLETES BUT ALSO WORKERS AND ROLE MODELS WHO HAVE HELPED
BUILD THE LEAGUE'S SUCCESS. >> THEY ARE NOW IN THEIR SIXTH
ROUND OF CONTRACT TALKS ASKING FOR FAIR PAY AND RESPECT FOR
THEIR HARD WORK EVEN AS THE WNBA GROWS.
PLAYERS STILL DON'T RECEIVE SHARE REVENUE FROM TICKETS,
SPONSORSHIPS OR TV DEALS WHILE MEN'S LEAGUES LIKE THE NBA
SHARE AROUND HALF THE PLAYERS ARE CALLING FOR RECOGNITION OF
THEIR VALUE AND THE SAME RESPECT GIVEN TO OTHER
PROFESSIONAL ATHLETES. WOMEN'S SPORTS BRING PEOPLE
TOGETHER, BOOST LOCAL ECONOMIES AND INSPIRE THE NEXT GENERATION
. >> THE GOLDEN STATE VALKYRIES
WILL CONTINUE TO ADD NEW ENERGY AND EXCITEMENT TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND SHOW YOUNG WOMEN WHAT IS POSSIBLE WHEN WOMEN ARE
SUPPORTED IN THE COMING YEARS. >> SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS
STOOD WITH WORKERS FIGHTING FOR FAIR TREATMENT AND I WANT TO
THANK THE S.F. LABOR COUNCIL FOR HELPING TO BRING THIS
RESOLUTION FORWARD. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR JAN SUBMIT SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
THANK YOU, MADAM. THANK YOU, MADAM CARD.
I HAVE IN MEMORIAM. >> COLLEAGUE I WOULD LIKE TO
OFFER AN IN MEMORIAM TO HECTOR .
>> HECTOR WILLIAMS A LONG TIME RESIDENTS AND HOMEOWNER IN THE
EXCELSIOR DISTRICT WHO PASSED AWAY PEACEFULLY ON OCTOBER 3RD,
2025 AT AGE 80. IN THE EARLY 1950S THERE WERE
FOUR YOUNG BROTHERS HECTOR TONY GILBERT AND RAY.
>> BORN AND RAISED IN A RURAL COPPER MINING TOWN IN NORTHERN
MEXICO VERY CLOSE IN AGE. >> THEY WERE AS CLOSE AS
BROTHERS COULD BE. WHY THEIR MOTHER WORKED LONG
HOURS TO SUPPORT HER FAMILY. >> HECTOR, THE ELDEST OF THIS
BROTHERS LOOKED AFTER HIS YOUNGER SIBLINGS WITH A
WATCHFUL EYE. >> WHENEVER HECTOR'S BABY
BROTHER RAYMOND KWAI HECTOR ACQUIRED HIM GENTLY AS BIG
BROTHER BABY SISTERS DO. BUT AS FAYE WOULD HAVE IT, THE
TOYS FOUND THEMSELVES EMBARKING ON THE LONG TRIP WHICH WOULD
CHANGE THE COURSE OF ALL THEIR LIVES FOREVER.
UPON ARRIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO, HECTOR WAS ENROLLED IN AND
PROUDLY GRADUATED FROM MISSION HIGH SCHOOL.
>> DURING THIS FORMATIVE YEARS HE BECAME A MENTOR AND THEN A
CERTIFIED CAMP COUNSELOR AT THE SALVATION ARMY'S RESCUE BOYS
CLUB SUMMER CAMP. >> NOW A YOUNG ADULT, HECTOR
HAD A STRONG AFFINITY FOR ALL THINGS AUTOMOTIVE.
>> HE TRAINED FOR SEVERAL YEARS AS AN AUTO MECHANIC, EVENTUALLY
FOUND AND OPERATED HIS OWN REPAIR SHOP.
AS ENGINE ALWAYS A RACING CAR AND THROUGH IT A RACING CAR
AND THROUGH IT AND HE BOUGHT A BIG THING IN YOUR FACE 1957
CHEVROLET BUT AIR WHICH HE NAMED TRIGGER.
IT WAS HIS TREASURE POSSESSIONS.
HAD I HAD A GIFT FOR FIXING THINGS WHEN SOMEONE WAS IN NEED
FOR CAR REPAIR HE UNSELFISHLY OFFERED TO REPAIR IT AND DID
NOT EXPECT TO BE COMPENSATED. HECTOR LOVED MUSIC.
HE LOVED TO TRAVEL. HE WAS FREE.
HE WAS A FERVENT SAN FRANCISCAN 40 NINERS AND ALSO SAN
FRANCISCO GIANTS FAN WATCHING HIS GRANDCHILDREN GROW UP
AND GETTING TO KNOW HIS GREAT GRANDCHILDREN AND FOR HIM
AND THIS JOY HE WAS AN EXCELLENT EXAMPLE OF WHAT A BIG
BROTHER SHOULD BE. >> HE OFFERED A LOAN OF OF
MONEY IF YOU FOUND YOURSELF TEMPORARILY INSOLVENT, OFFER
YOU A PLACE TO STAY IF YOU EXPERIENCING ONE OF YOUR LIFE'S
UNEXPECTED RAOUL PATCH AND GAVE YOU SAGE ADVICE WHEN YOU ASKED
FOR IT OR NOT. >> AS HIS BUSINESS THRIVE,
HECTOR ACHIEVED TO COVER AMERICAN DREAMS AND WAS ABLE TO
PURCHASE A HOME IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR HIS GROWING
FAMILY. HECTOR WAS A KIND,
COMPASSIONATE EVEN TEMPERED WOULD CONSIDER CONSIDERATE
FAMILY MAN AND GOOD CITIZEN WHO WAS NON-JUDGMENTAL.
>> HE REMAINED HE REMINDED US THAT LOVE IS HARD TO COME BY
AND TO ACCEPT PEOPLE AS THEY ARE.
HECTOR IS SURVIVED BY HIS CHILDREN DANNY MICHAEL FOR
REBECCA AND AS WELL AS HIS THREE BROTHERS A SISTER
AND GRANDCHILDREN'S GREAT GRANDCHILD JANE'S NIECES
AND NEPHEW. HECTOR LEAVES BEHIND A FAMILY
WHO WILL FOREVER BE PROUD TO CALL HIM DARE'S.
MAY HE IN REST IN PEACE. >> THERE WAS I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES, I WOULD ASK THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING ON
BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN REMEMBRANCE OF A
LONGTIME PUBLIC SERVANT IN CRIMINAL JUSTICE INNOVATOR
WHO LEFT AN ENDURING INFLUENCE ON SAN FRANCISCO AND ITS LEGAL
COMMUNITY AMONG ITS POLITICAL POLITICAL LEADERS AND IN A CITY
THAT IS IN A NUMBER OF WAYS BETTER FOR HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO
IT. >> ARLO SMITH, WHO SERVED AS
SAN FRANCISCO'S DISTRICT ATTORNEY FROM 1980 TO 1996,
PASSED AWAY EARLIER THIS MONTH. HE WAS 98 YEARS OLD.
ARLO WAS AMONG MY FIRST BOSSES AFTER I GRADUATED COLLEGE
AND HE WAS AN EARLY AND INFLUENTIAL MENTOR TO ME
FOR HIS TIRELESS WORK TO DO JUSTICE FOR HIS COMMITMENT TO
PROTECTING PUBLIC SAFETY AND FOR HIS FEARLESS EFFORTS TO
UPLIFT AND EMPOWER THOSE FROM UNDERREPRESENTED AND TOO OFTEN
MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES. LONG BEFORE A GENERATION OF
ENLIGHTENED CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORMERS WOULD EMBRACE WORTHY
CONCEPTS LIKE DIVERSITY, EQUITY AND INCLUSION.
THEY WERE PERSONAL PRIORITIES FOR ARLO SMITH, WHO AS A GOOD
MAN WITH AN ABIDING SENSE OF FAIRNESS SOUGHT TO INCLUDE
THOSE FROM ALL OUR CITY'S DIVERSE COMMUNITIES BECAUSE IT
WAS THE RIGHT THING TO DO AS A DISTRICT ATTORNEY AND AS A
POLITICAL LEADER. ARLO SMITH HIRED AND PROMOTED
MANY DEDICATED WOMEN PEOPLE OF COLOR AND MEMBERS OF THE LGBTQ
PLUS COMMUNITY MYSELF INCLUDED TO POSITIONS OF LEADERSHIP
AND RESPONSIBILITY. AT A TIME WHEN THERE WEREN'T
MANY OF US THERE, THE NAMES OF THOSE GIVEN OPPORTUNITIES BY
ARLO SMITH ARE COUNTLESS BUT THEY INCLUDE ADMIRED LEGAL
COMMUNITY LEADERS RANGING FROM JUDGE JULIE TANG TO A THEN BABY
LAWYER NAMED YVONNE MORAIS WHO TODAY SERVES AS OUR OWN CHIEF
DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY. THEY INCLUDE TWO BELOVED
COMMUNITY MEMBERS WHO ARE NO LONGER WITH US.
HAITI READ FROM SAN FRANCISCO'S BLACK COMMUNITY IN WAYNE FRIDAY
AND DENNIS COLLINS FROM THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY.
ARLO TRUSTED ME EARLY IN MY CAREER TO MANAGE HIS SUCCESSFUL
1991 REELECTION BID A YEAR AFTER HIS NARROW LOSS AS THE
DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE FOR CALIFORNIA ATTORNEY GENERAL A
RACE HE LOST BY JUST ONE VOTE PER PRECINCT STATEWIDE.
AS HIS SPEECHWRITER FOR SEVERAL YEARS I WORKED HARD TO LEARN
ARLO'S VOICE BUT I BENEFITED MOST FROM LEARNING HIS VALUES.
LOOKING BACK ON IT TODAY I AM ESPECIALLY GRATEFUL TO ARLO FOR
AFFORDING ME THE OPPORTUNITY AT A YOUNG AGE TO WORK WITH HIM
WHEN HE CREATED THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY'S HATE CRIMES TASK
FORCE IN 1991 TO DEVELOP PROTOCOLS FOR PROSECUTING
CRIMES THAT TARGET NOT SOLELY VICTIMS BUT ENTIRE COMMUNITIES
. IT WAS THERE I FIRST CAME TO
LEARN ABOUT THE INSPIRING DIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO AT
ITS BEST AND HOW OUR CITY'S ECLECTIC COMMUNITIES CAN RALLY
AROUND ONE ANOTHER ON UNIFYING ISSUES LIKE PROTECTING THE
SAFETY OF OUR MOST VULNERABLE AND STANDING UP TO
DISCRIMINATION AND BIGOTRY. THE HATE CRIMES TASK FORCE WAS
IN FACT AMONG SEVERAL PIONEERING FIRSTS ARLO SMITH
LED AS DISTRICT ATTORNEY. OTHERS WERE A GROUNDBREAKING
VICTIM SERVICES DIVISION AND A DOMESTIC VIOLENCE UNIT THAT WAS
AMONG THE FIRST OF ITS KIND IN THE NATION.
THAT'S ESPECIALLY WORTH NOTING AS WE CELEBRATE LEADING WITH
COURAGE TODAY IN RECOGNIZING DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AWARENESS
MONTH. OUR HEARTFELT CONDOLENCES TO
THOSE ARE TO THOSE ARLO SMITH LEAVES BEHIND HIS LOVING
CHILDREN. ARLO ACE AND DAUGHTER IN LAW
LAURA THOMAS AND ALEXA HIS GRANDCHILDREN MINA SOHA
AND ABRAHAM HALE AND HIS GREAT GRANDCHILDREN TIGHE HALE
AND NORA LILY. REST IN PEACE, ARLO.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE TO OUR CITY AND FOR THE
INSPIRATION YOUR LIFE AND LEADERSHIP WERE TO ME
AND TO THE COUNTLESS OTHERS TO WHOM YOU GAVE THEIR START
IN PUBLIC SERVICE. AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR
FIELDER. >> >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES. IT IS WITH A HEAVY HEART THAT I
SHARE THIS IN MEMORIAM FOR BONO'S BUT A FOR BUDA TOKI.
BONO'S WAS A CHERISHED RESIDENT OF BERNAL HEIGHTS AND THE
NEPALI COMMUNITY IN THE BAY AREA.
HIS LIFE WAS TRAGICALLY CUT SHORT BY A HIT AND RUN DRIVER
ON OCTOBER FOURTH, 2025 AT THE CORNER OF CORTLAND AVENUE
AND ANDERSON IN BERNAL HEIGHTS. AS HE WAS WALKING HOME AFTER
CELEBRATING THE TRAIN FESTIVAL ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT
FESTIVALS IN NEPAL CELEBRATED EACH FALL TO COMMEMORATE THE
VICTORY VICTORY OF GOOD OVER EVIL.
>> THIS INCIDENT MARKS THE 13TH PEDESTRIAN DEATH IN SAN
FRANCISCO THIS YEAR. >> BONO'S WAS KIND, HARDWORKING
AND A LIGHT HEARTED YOUNG MAN WHO BROUGHT WARMTH
AND POSITIVITY TO EVERYONE HE MET.
HE WAS A DEVOTED FATHER LOVING BROTHER AND LOYAL FRIEND.
KNOWN FOR HIS HUMILITY, KINDNESS AND DEDICATION TO
HELPING OTHERS. ORIGINALLY FROM NEPAL HE BECAME
A PROUD SAN FRANCISCAN AND AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE NEPALI
AMERICAN DIASPORA IN THE BAY. >> EMBODYING THE VALUES OF
COMPASSION, FAMILY AND PERSEVERANCE SUPPORTING HIS
FAMILY HERE AND IN NEPAL. >> HIS WARMTH, GENEROSITY
AND QUIET STRENGTH TOUCHED MANY AND HIS LEGACY WILL CONTINUE TO
INSPIRE THOSE WHO SEEK TO MAKE THEIR COMMUNITIES STRONGER
AND MORE UNITED. AT THE MEMORIAL SERVICE,
COUNCIL MEMBER DILLIE BATARI OF HERCULES, THE FIRST ELECTED
OFFICIALS FROM THE NEPALI AMERICAN COMMUNITY
IN CALIFORNIA OFFERED HEARTFELT REMEMBRANCES HONORING BURNS'S
LIFE AND CONTRIBUTIONS, EMPHASIZING HIS EXAMPLE OF
RESILIENCE AND EFFORTS TO BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER IN THE DAYS
FOLLOWING HIS DEATH. BERNAL RESIDENTS FAMILY,
FRIENDS AND ELECTEDS GATHERED IN BERNAL HEIGHTS TO HONOR
BONO'S IN RESPONSE TO THE SENSELESS AND TRAGIC INCIDENT.
I HELD A MEETING WITH BERNAL NEIGHBORS AFTER THE ACCIDENT
AND ASKED AS IF PITY M.T.A. AND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO
ATTEND AND AFFIRM THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO MAKING BERNAL
STREETS SAFER IN BONO'S MEMORY. I WANT TO EXTEND MY DEEPEST
CONDOLENCES TO BONO'S EIGHT YEAR OLD DAUGHTER BROTHER
AND OF BEING BUDA TOKI THE BUDDHA TOKI FAMILY IN NEPAL
AND THE NEPALI COMMUNITY IN THE BAY AREA.
MAY BONO'S HIS MEMORY CONTINUED TO REMIND US OF THE POWER OF
KINDNESS UNITY AND THE COLLECTIVE PURSUIT OF A SAFER
AND MORE COMPASSIONATE SAN FRANCISCO.
I ALSO HAVE OTHER INTRODUCTIONS TODAY I AM EXCITED TO INTRODUCE
A RESOLUTION URGING THE MAYOR, TREASURER AND TAX COLLECTOR
AND OTHER DEPARTMENTS TO EXPLORE AND PURSUE FUNDING
OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT OF SAN FRANCISCO
GREEN BANK. >> THIS RESOLUTION BUILDS ON AN
EARLIER PLAN UNANIMOUSLY APPROVED BY THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WHICH INITIATED THE DEVELOPMENT OF A PLAN FOR A
PUBLIC BANK. THIS NEW RESOLUTION
INCORPORATES LESSONS LEARNED FROM SAN FRANCISCANS ALIGNING
THE DEVELOPMENT PLAN WITH HOW SAN FRANCISCANS WANT THE BANK
TO FUNCTION. RECENT POLLING SHOWS THAT 67%
OF LIKELY VOTERS ARE IN FAVOR OF STARTING A PUBLIC BANK
AND AN EVEN HIGHER PERCENTAGE OF LIKELY VOTERS 70% ARE
IN FAVOR OF A GREEN BANK. GREEN BANKS ARE NONPROFIT
FINANCING ENTITIES WHICH HAVE A FOCUS ON PROVIDING FINANCING
FOR RENEWABLE ENERGY INFRASTRUCTURE INFRASTRUCTURE
THAT OFTEN STRUGGLES TO FIND FINANCING NOW.
>> IN ADDITION TO SUPPORTING LOCAL ENTERPRISE AND AFFORDABLE
HOUSING, THE GREEN BANK WILL BE CRITICAL FOR SAN FRANCISCO'S
FIGHT AGAINST THE WORSENING EFFECTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE
AND WILL ALSO PROVIDE RELIABLE FINANCING FOR AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PROJECTS. >> AS WE ALL HEARD AT
YESTERDAY'S LAND USE MEETING DISCUSSING THE FAMILY ZONING
PLAN, WE ARE IN DIRE NEED FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING FINANCING
AND A GREEN BANK IS ONE SOLUTION.
>> THIS RESOLUTION MARKS A STEP FORWARD AND NOT JUST ADDRESSING
THE PROBLEMS OF FINANCING PROJECTS BUT DEVELOPING A
FINANCIAL INSTITUTION THAT IS ACCOUNTABLE TO ITS OWNERS THE
PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO. AS WORKING SAN FRANCISCANS
STRUGGLE WITH THE RISING COST OF LIVING AND THE GROWING
THREAT OF THE CLIMATE CRISIS. WE NEED PUBLIC INSTITUTIONS
THAT ASPIRE TO REIMAGINE HOW WE INVEST IN OUR COMMUNITIES
AND IN SOLUTIONS THAT ADDRESS CLIMATE CHANGE AND HOUSING
INSECURITY. I WANT TO THANK THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC BANK COALITION LAST CO EXECUTIVE OFFICER
COLLEGE SAMURAI FORMER SUPERVISOR DEAN PRESTON, THE
TREASURER AND TAX COLLECTOR, COMPTROLLER AND CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICES FOR ALL OF YOUR WORK AND COLLABORATION ON THIS
RESOLUTION. I ALSO WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISORS CHAN CHEN, MAHMOOD AND WALTON FOR YOUR EARLY
CO-SPONSORSHIP. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
REQUESTING A HEARING REGARDING OUTSTANDING FINANCIAL
COMMITMENTS MADE BY PRIVATE DEVELOPERS IN SEEKING SUPPORT
FOR THE HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS AT 2000 BRYANT STREET AND 681
FLORIDA STREET IN THE MISSION DISTRICT.
IN 2016 DEVELOPER NICK PODELL AND HIS REPRESENTATIVES CAME
BEFORE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AFTER MEETING WITH FORMER
DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR DAVID CAMPOS AND COMMUNITY
STAKEHOLDERS REGARDING THE MARKET RATE DEVELOPMENT AT 2000
2070 BRYANT STREET AND THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
AT 681 FLORIDA STREET. >> DURING A SEQUEL APPEAL MR.
PADDLES PROJECT MR. PADILLA'S ATTORNEY AFFIRMED MULTIPLE
TIMES AND SUBMITTED A LETTER FROM MR. FIDEL CONFIRMING THAT
MR. PADILLA'S DEVELOPMENT GROUP WOULD PROVIDE $500,000
IN CAPITAL FUNDING FOR TENANT IMPROVEMENTS TO THE COMMUNITY
ART SPACE ON THE GROUND FLOOR OF 68 ONE FLORIDA STREET ONE OF
SEVERAL CONCESSIONS TO THE COMMUNITY CONCERNS.
>> FAST FORWARD TO TODAY AND BOTH HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS
ARE OCCUPIED INCLUDING THE GROUND FLOOR SPACE OF 681
FLORIDA STREET BY THROUGH THAT E ALTERNATIVA DE LAS AMERICAS
OR BETTER KNOWN AS GHANA. THE ORGANIZATION RESPONSIBLE
FOR MANY OF THE CITY'S CULTURAL CELEBRATIONS AND CEREMONIES
INCLUDING THE ANNUAL CARNIVAL FESTIVAL GHANA AND THE
COMMUNITY WHO RELIED ON THE DEVELOPER'S COMMITMENTS HAVE
YET TO SEE THE FULFILLMENT OF THE FINANCIAL PROMISE TO FUND
THEIR CAPITAL IMPROVEMENTS DESPITE REPEATED ATTEMPTS BY
THE CURRENT OWNERS OF 681 FLORIDA STREET AND MY OFFICE,
MR. PRADELLE NOR THE CURRENT OWNER OF 2000 BRYANT STREET
HAVE HEEDED CALLS ABOUT THEIR OUTSTANDING COMMITMENTS.
I AM HOPEFUL THAT WE CAN MAKE THIS RIGHT.
I'M CALLING FOR A HEARING ON THIS MATTER AND REQUESTING THAT
NICK PADDLE GERY PARTNERS T&E SEE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT AND THE
CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE REPORT AND EXCUSE ME.
FINALLY COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM ANNOUNCING A HEARING ON THE
OPEN GOVERNMENT TRACT AWARDED BY THE MAYOR'S OFFICE IN THEIR
EFFORT TO STAND UP A SYSTEM TO LAUNCH THE PERMIT S F PROGRAM.
MY CONCERNS AROUND THE OPEN GOV CONTRACT BOIL DOWN TO THE
QUALITY OF THE CONTRACT THE COSTS, THE PROCESS BY WHICH IT
WAS PROCURED AND THE PREEXISTING RELATIONSHIPS OF
OPEN GOV WITH THE MAYOR'S FORMER NONPROFIT TIPPING POINT.
FIRSTLY CLARITY A COMPETITOR TO OPEN GOV WAS CONSISTENTLY RATED
HIGHER BY CITY STAFFERS THAN OPEN GOV SCORING AN AVERAGE OF
4.42 OUT OF FIVE WHILE OPEN GOV SCORED JUST 2.8.
FEEDBACK FROM 16 TECHNICAL CITY STAFFERS ALSO STATED THAT OPEN
GOALS TECHNOLOGY HAD QUOTE GAPS SO SIGNIFICANT THAT IT QUOTE
SHOULDN'T BE CONSIDERED. SECONDLY OPEN GOV WILL COST THE
CITY UP TO $4 MILLION ANNUALLY ALMOST EIGHT TIMES AS MUCH THE
LICENSE OF CLARITY WHICH WOULD HAVE COST THE CITY JUST 528,000
PER YEAR. THIRDLY, ACCORDING TO THE S.F.
CHRONICLE, THE CONTRACT WAS AWARDED UNDER AN UNUSUAL
PROCESS UNDER A LITTLE KNOWN SECTION OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE THAT BYPASSES THE STANDARD BIDDING PROCESS.
AND LASTLY, BOTH THE CHRONICLE AND THE STANDARD HAVE REPORTED
THAT LEADERS FROM OPEN GOV HAVE LONGSTANDING RELATIONSHIPS WITH
THE MAYOR. THE MAYOR'S FORMER NONPROFIT
TIPPING POINT. ANY ONE OF THESE CIRCUMSTANCES
IS OF THIS CONTRACT AWARD ON THEIR OWN ARE EYEBROW RAISING.
BUT COMBINED THEY ARE CAUSE FOR SERIOUS CONCERN.
I'M COMMITTED TO BRINGING TRANSPARENCY, INTEGRITY
AND EFFICIENCY TO CITY HALL. THAT IS WHY AS CHAIR OF THE
GOVERNMENT AND AUDIT OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE I CALL FOR THIS
HEARING. I ALSO WANT TO TAKE THIS MOMENT
TO REMIND THE PUBLIC THAT ANYONE WITH REPORTS OF WASTE,
FRAUD OR ABUSE BY CITY EMPLOYEES AND PEOPLE WHO DO
BUSINESS WITH THE CITY CAN MAKE A CONFIDENTIAL WHISTLEBLOWER
COMPLAINT WITH THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE AND IT
WILL BE INVESTIGATED. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES, YOU'VE OFTEN
HEARD ME TALK ABOUT DATA AND STATISTICS AND THERE'S ONE
NUMBER THAT I NOTE FREQUENTLY. >> IT'S 3530 500.
THERE ARE MORE THAN 3500 CHILDREN AND YOUTH LIVING
IN THE TENDERLOIN AND I SAY IT OFTEN BECAUSE IT WOULD SEEM
THAT NO MATTER HOW OFTEN I SAY IT, IT'S A DEMOGRAPHIC THAT
STILL FEELS INVISIBLE AND THE DIALOG AROUND THE NEIGHBORHOOD
IF I DON'T SAY IT THEN I FEAR LITTLE WILL CHANGE FOR THOSE
3500 CHILDREN AND YOUTH LIVING THERE AND THEY'LL CONTINUE TO
FACE DAILY EXPOSURE TO UNSAFE STREET CONDITIONS, DRUG
ACTIVITY, OVERDOSES AND VIOLENCE.
AT LEAST 57 YOUTH AGED 13 TO 17 HAVE BEEN ARRESTED IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR DRUG DEALING SINCE AUGUST 2023.
OFTEN IN THE TENDERLOIN IN FACT, JUST EARLIER THIS YEAR
IN FEBRUARY 2ND MEN WERE CHARGED IN SAN FRANCISCO
SUPERIOR COURT WITH USING A MINOR TO DISTRIBUTE NARCOTICS
IN THE TENDERLOIN, UNDERSCORING ACTIVE RECRUITMENT OF YOUTH
INTO THE LOCAL DRUG TRADE. >> WHETHER YOU'RE INVOLVED
IN THE DRUG ACTIVITY OR VIOLENCE, JUST LIVING AROUND
THESE CONDITIONED COMPOUND COMPOUNDS AND EXACERBATES
PUBLIC HEALTH DISPARITIES AFFECTING OUR YOUTH, THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH IS CLEAR THAT VIOLENCE IS A PUBLIC
HEALTH ISSUE THAT CAUSES INJURY ,DEATH AND CHRONIC TRAUMA WITH
EFFECTS LIKE TOXIC STRESS, POST-TRAUMATIC STRESS DISORDER
AND LONG TERM PHYSICAL AND MENTAL HEALTH HARM AMONG
YOUTH EXPOSED TO COMMUNITY VIOLENCE.
>> WE HAVE TO DO BETTER. WE OWE THEM SO MUCH MORE THAN
THAT. >> THE DATA IS CLEAR AS
REPORTED BY THIS MORNING BY MISSION LOCAL YOUTH VIOLENCE
PREVENTION PROGRAMS IMPLEMENTED IN THE BAYVIEW IN RECENT YEARS
HAVE CUT VIOLENT CRIME BY 50%. THAT'S NOT JUST A STATISTIC
IT'S LIVES SAVED. >> BUT NO SUCH PROGRAM IN THE
TENDERLOIN EXISTS. AND THE IMPACT IS REAL.
>> IN THE PAST TWO MONTHS ALONE I'VE ATTENDED TWO SERVICES TO
MOURN THE LOSS OF SONS OF OUR NEIGHBORHOOD LOST TWO SOON TO
AN OVERDOSE AND ANOTHER TO GUN VIOLENCE.
>> THESE YOUNG MEN DESERVE THE CHANCE TO LIVE A FULL LIFE
AND NO FAMILY SHOULD HAVE TO BURY THEIR CHILD BECAUSE OF
PREVENTABLE VIOLENCE IN OUR STREETS.
>> THE COMMUNITY WILL NEVER BE SAME AGAIN.
WHEN I SPOKE TO THEIR GRIEVING FAMILIES IN THE HOSPITAL, THEIR
PAIN WAS SIMPLY UNFATHOMABLE. >> WHILE I WISH I COULD CARRY
THEIR PAIN FOR THEM, WHAT I PROMISED THEM I COULD DO WAS
CHANNEL THEIR LOSS INTO ACTION DAY IN AND DAY OUT FOR A
BETTER, SAFER FUTURE SO NO FAMILY HAS TO ENDURE WHAT THEY
HAVE GONE THROUGH. >> AND SO TODAY I'M CALLING TO
LAUNCH A TENDERLOIN YOUTH VIOLENCE PREVENTION PROGRAM
BECAUSE EVERY YOUNG PERSON DESERVES A CHANCE AT LIFE.
>> AND COLLEAGUES, I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU TO THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN, YOUTH AND FAMILIES
AND THEIR FAMILIES AND TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF VICTIMS
RIGHTS ESPECIALLY ABBY LEE AND BOBBY LOPEZ FOR THE
INCREDIBLE WORK YOU DO EVERY DAY ACROSS OUR CITY TO SUPPORT
YOUNG PEOPLE, SURVIVORS, FAMILIES AND YOU FOR YOUR
THOUGHTFUL FEEDBACK AND HELPING SHAPE THIS RESOLUTION.
>> A HEARTFELT THANK YOU AS WELL TO YOSEF AZEEM AND STEPHEN
BATTS IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR THEIR FEEDBACK
AND COLLABORATION IN DRAFTING THIS RESOLUTION.
>> FINALLY, WE ARE GRATEFUL TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR
THEIR ONGOING EFFORTS THROUGH THE TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY ACTION
PLAN WHICH PROVIDES A STRONG FOUNDATION FOR US TO CONTINUE
BUILDING UPON AS WE WORK COLLECTIVELY TOWARDS SAFETY,
HEALING AND OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL YOUNG PEOPLE IN THE TENDERLOIN
AND ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU TO UNITED PLAYERS
GCF AND I'D LIKE TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM LOGAN
AND MY OFFICE FOR DRAFTING THIS RESOLUTION AS WELL.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. SUPERVISOR MENDELSON.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
WALTON FOR THE SCOOTER ENFORCEMENT LEGISLATION.
THERE'S A BUNCH OF PEOPLE IN DISTRICT EIGHT JUMPING OUT
OF THEIR SEATS IN SUPPORT OF THAT I THINK BUT I IMAGINE
OTHER DISTRICTS AS WELL. AND THEN I ALSO WANT TO THANK
SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR THAT REALLY BEAUTIFUL IN MEMORIAM
FOR FOR ARLO SMITH. AND MADAM CLERK, WHAT DO YOU
NEED ME TO DO ANYTHING TO MAKE THAT?
>> YES, MR. PRESIDENT JUST STATED FOR THE RECORD THAT IT
WILL BE ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD ALL DOWN.
>> THAT IN MEMORIAM WILL BE ON BEHALF OF THE FULL BOARD
AND I'LL GAVEL THAT. >> OKAY.
AND THEN COLLEAGUES, I HAVE A COUPLE OF RESOLUTIONS AND MORE
IN MEMORIAM THAN I WOULD LIKE. ALL RIGHT.
FIRST I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION SUPPORTING THE BAY
AREA AIR DISTRICTS RULES THAT ESTABLISH ZERO EMISSION
STANDARDS FOR BUILDING APPLIANCES.
IN MARCH OF 2023 THE BAY AREA AIR DISTRICT ADOPTED RULES NINE
FOUR AND NINE SIX. THESE RULES ESTABLISHED FUTURE
ZERO EMISSION STANDARDS FOR WATER HEATERS AND FURNACES
WHICH WILL CUT DEADLY AIR POLLUTION AND MAKE ENERGY BILLS
MORE AFFORDABLE. THE RULES WILL ONLY APPLY WHEN
EXISTING FOSSIL FUEL EQUIPMENT NEEDS REPLACEMENT AND WILL
PHASE OUT PHASED IN GRADUALLY STARTING IN 2027 FOR WATER
HEATERS IN 2029 FOR FURNACES. THESE RULES WILL PROVIDE
SIGNIFICANT HEALTH BENEFITS FOR THE BAY AREA WHICH HAS SOME OF
THE WORST AIR QUALITY IN THE NATION.
THE RULES WOULD LIKELY PREVENT 15,000 ASTHMA ATTACKS ANNUALLY
AND SAVE UP TO $890 MILLION IN ANNUAL HEALTH CARE COSTS
ATTRIBUTABLE TO AIR POLLUTION EXPOSURE.
SWITCHING FROM GAS TO HEAT PUMPS CAN ALSO SAVE RATEPAYERS
$370 PER YEAR ON THEIR ENERGY BILLS.
AHEAD OF THE 2027 IMPLEMENTATION DATE, THE AIR
DISTRICT IS WORKING TO AMEND THESE RULES TO INCLUDE COMMON
SENSE FLEXIBILITY MEASURES. UNSURPRISINGLY, THE FOSSIL FUEL
INDUSTRY AND ITS ALLIES ARE HOPING TO USE THIS PROCESS TO
ROLL BACK THESE CLEAN AIR RULES ENTIRELY.
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH COMMUNITY CLIMATE AND ENVIRONMENTAL
JUSTICE GROUPS ARE MOBILIZING TOO TO PROTECT THESE RULES
WHILE WORKING WITH STAFF TO INCORPORATE MEASURES TO HELP
ENSURE SMOOTH AND EQUITABLE IMPLEMENTATION.
THE RESOLUTION SUPPORTS THE AIR DISTRICTS WORK TO RESPONSIBLY
AMEND AND IMPLEMENT THOSE THESE RULES SO THAT WE CAN HAVE A
CLEANER AND HEALTHIER BAY AREA FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE AND THANK SUPERVISORS WALTON AND MAHMUD
MAHMOOD FOR THEIR SERVICE ON THE AIR DISTRICT BOARD OF
DIRECTORS AND THEN I WANT TO THANK SAM FISHMAN AND COLLEEN
CORRIGAN FROM THE BAY AREA CLEAN AIR COALITION AND FOR
WORKING WITH CALVIN IN MY OFFICE ON THIS RESOLUTION AND.
>> AND THEN I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE CLIMATE EMERGENCY
COALITION FOR THEIR PERSISTENT ADVOCACY ON THESE ISSUES
AND FINALLY S.F. ENVIRONMENT FOR THEIR HELPFUL FEEDBACK ON
THE RESOLUTION. NEXT I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE OCTOBER 28TH, 2025 AS ROGER CASEMENT
DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO. ROGER CASEMENT WAS A GAY MAN
WHO LIVED FROM 1864 TO 1916 AND IS KNOWN FOR EXPOSING THE
ATROCITIES OF COLONIALISM IN THE CONGO AND PERU AND FOR
HIS MARTYRDOM AFTER THE 1916 EASTER UPRISING IN IRELAND.
HIS 1904 CASEMENT REPORT DESCRIBED THE ATROCITIES
COMMITTED BY KING LEOPOLD THE SECOND OF BELGIUM
AND CONTRIBUTED TO THE END OF LEOPOLD'S REIGN OF TERROR
IN THE CONGO, THUS HELPING END THE ABUSE OF THE CONGOLESE
INCLUDING THE ENSLAVEMENT, MUTILATION AND TORTURE OF
NATIVES ON RUBBER PLANTATIONS. CASEMENT WAS ORIGINALLY
INDICTED BY BRITAIN IN 1911 FOR HIS INVESTIGATIONS INTO HUMAN
RIGHTS ATROCITIES AND THE RUBBER INDUSTRY IN PERU.
BUT AFTER HE WAS CONVICTED OF TREASON FOR HIS WORK TO SUPPORT
IRISH INDEPENDENCE PRIOR TO THE 1916 EASTER RISING, HIS TITLE
WAS STRIPPED. HE WAS EXECUTED BY HANGING
AND HIS BODY WAS THROWN INTO A PRISON CEMETERY TO HONOR HIS
MEMORY. THE CONSULATE GENERAL OF
IRELAND, NEALE RICHMOND, IRELAND'S MINISTER OF STATE FOR
INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND DIASPORA AND THE RAINBOW
HONOR WALK WILL BE UNVEILING A COMMEMORATIVE BRONZE PLAQUE TO
HONOR HIS LEGACY ON OCTOBER 28TH IN THE CASTRO.
I WOULD BE REMISS IF IN ADDITION TO THE FINE FOLKS
OF THE CONSULATE AND THE RAINBOW HONOR WALK I DID NOT
OFFER SPECIAL ACKNOWLEDGMENTS TO MATTHEW ROTHSCHILD WHO FOR
AT LEAST A DECADE MAYBE LONGER HAS BEEN CAMPAIGNING TO SEE HIS
HERO ROGER CASEMENT GET THIS RECOGNITION.
THANKS. SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR YOUR
CO-SPONSORSHIP. YOUR FRIENDSHIP WITH MELANIE
ROTHSCHILD AND YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP OF THIS
RESOLUTION. AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK HONORE
FOR ALL HIS WORK ON THIS. THE FIRST IN MEMORIAM I HAVE IS
FOR MISS MAJOR GRIFFIN GRACIE WHO DIED ON OCTOBER 13TH AT THE
AGE OF 78. MISS MAJOR WAS BORN IN CHICAGO
ON OCTOBER 25TH, 1946. SHE WAS ASSIGNED MALE AT BIRTH
BUT KNEW FROM AN EARLY AGE THAT HER TRUE GENDER WAS FEMALE
DESPITE NOT HAVING THE LANGUAGE TO DESCRIBE IT AT THE TIME
IN THE LATE 50S SHE PUBLICLY CAME OUT AS TRANS.
SHE SPENT THE NEXT 20 YEARS OF HER LIFE IN AND OUT OF
HOMELESSNESS ON WELFARE AND RECEIVING HORMONE DRUGS
FROM THE BLACK MARKET. AFTER SHE WAS EXPELLED FROM
COLLEGE AT 16 FOR WEARING WOMEN'S CLOTHING, MISS MAJOR
BEGAN WORKING AS A SHOWGIRL AT THE JEWEL BOX REVUE AT THE
APOLLO THEATER IN CHICAGO AND TOOK UP SEX WORK.
FIRST THE STEADY INCOME. DURING THIS TIME POLICE RAIDS
ON GAY BARS WERE COMMON AND TRANS WOMEN WERE OFTEN
ROUNDED UP AND SENT TO POLICE STATIONS INSTEAD OF JAIL.
SHE WAS INCARCERATED AT A PSYCHIATRIC FACILITY.
SHE LATER MOVED TO NEW YORK WHERE SHE WAS A REGULAR PATRON
OF THE STONEWALL INN. WHEN POLICE RAIDED THE BAR
IN THE EARLY HOURS OF JUNE 28TH 1969, SHE WAS AMONG THE FIRST
TO FIGHT BACK. THE STONEWALL RIOTS LASTED SIX
DAYS AND KICKSTARTED THE MODERN GAY RIGHTS MOVEMENT.
IN THE 70S AFTER THE DEATH OF A FRIEND WHO SHE SUSPECTED WAS
MURDERED BY A CLIENT, SHE AND FELLOW SEX WORKERS BANDED
TOGETHER TO LOOK OUT FOR EACH OTHER SINCE THEY DIDN'T BELIEVE
THE POLICE OR ANYONE ELSE WAS GOING TO LOOK OUT FOR THEM.
>> SHE DESCRIBED THIS AS THE START OF HER ACTIVISM.
IN 1974, AFTER SERVING TIME IN A MEN'S PRISON FOR A
ROBBERY, SHE BECAME AN ADVOCATE FOR INCARCERATED TRANS PEOPLE.
SHE MOVED TO SAN DIEGO IN THE LATE 70S.
THERE SHE JOINED THE FIGHT AGAINST AIDS AND SHE STARTED
THE HEALTH CARE AGENCY IN ANGELS OF CARE WHERE TRANS
WOMEN PROVIDED CARE FOR GAY MEN AND TRANS WOMEN DROPPED DYING
IN THE EPIDEMIC. MS. MAJOR CONTINUED HER AIDS
RELIEF WORK WHEN SHE MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO, BECOMING A
HEALTH EDUCATOR FOR THE TENDERLOIN AIDS RESOURCE CENTER
AND ADVOCATING FOR A MOBILE NEEDLE EXCHANGE PROGRAM.
SHE ALSO STARTED A DROP IN PROGRAM FOR TO PROTECT TRANS
SEX WORKERS CALLED GIGI'S PLACE .
IN 2005 SHE WAS BROUGHT ON AS THE FIRST EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF
THE TRANSGENDER GENDER VARIANT AND INTERSEX JUSTICE PROJECT
WHICH FIGHTS THE ABUSE OF TRANS PEOPLE OF COLOR IN PRISON A
ROLE SHE HELD UNTIL 2015. THROUGH THIS WORK SHE TESTIFIED
ON BEHALF OF TRANS PRISONERS BEFORE THE CALIFORNIA STATE
ASSEMBLY AS WELL AS THE UNITED NATIONS HUMAN RIGHTS COMMITTEE
IN GENEVA. MS. MAJOR SPENT HER FINAL YEARS
IN LITTLE ROCK, ARKANSAS, WHERE SHE FOUNDED HOUSE OF KEY TO
PROVIDE RESOURCES FOR BLACK TRANS LEADERS.
IN A 2023 INTERVIEW SHE SAID I KNOW THE WORLD I WOULD LIKE TO
LIVE IN. IT'S IN MY HEAD BUT I TRY MY
BEST TO LIVE IT NOW. REST IN PEACE AND POWER.
MS. MAJOR MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING.
>> I HAVE TWO MORE IN MEMORIAM THE LAST COUPLE IN MEMORIAM
IN MEMORIAM. THE LAST COUPLE OF MONTHS HAVE
BEEN ROUGH FOR THE NIGHTLIFE INDUSTRY AND COMMUNITY.
FIRST I'M ASKING THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING
IN MEMORY OF MARK RENNIE KNOWN AS THE BATMAN OF S.F. NIGHTLIFE
WHO DIED ON SEPTEMBER FIRST AT THE AGE OF 76.
HE WAS BORN IN BALTIMORE, MARYLAND ON MAY 23RD, 1949.
HE EARNED HIS BACHELOR OF ARTS DEGREE FROM THE FROM OHIO
UNIVERSITY IN 1971 AND GRADUATED FROM UC HASTINGS
COLLEGE OF LAW IN 1974. AFTER PASSING THE BAR HE OPENED
THE LAW OFFICES OF MAKI RENNIE WHERE HE HELPED THE CITY'S
DANCE CLUB OWNERS AND BARTENDERS NAVIGATE LEGAL
AND PERMITTING ISSUES IN THE EARLY 1980S WHEN THE SOUTH OF
MARKET NEIGHBORHOOD WAS EMERGING AS SAN FRANCISCO'S
NIGHTCLUB DISTRICT. MARK WAS THE OWNER OF THE
POPULAR CLUB NINE WHERE CHRIS ISAAC PERFORMED IN THE HOUSE
BAND AND COURTNEY LOVE WAS THE COAT CHECK ATTENDANT.
MARK WAS AN INTREPID ENTREPRENEUR AND BOUGHT 15
ABANDONED WAREHOUSES ON FOLSOM STREET TO CREATE ARTIST STUDIOS
AND OFFICE SPACES. HIS RESTAURANT THE BILLBOARD
CAFE FEATURED A WALL SIZE EXTERIOR ART AND WAS CONNECTED
TO EIGHT HOTEL ROOMS. TURN GALLERY IS CALLED THE ART
MOTEL. RENNIE ADVOCATED ON BEHALF OF
THE OF OF NIGHTCLUBS, ARTISTS, STREET FAIRS AND THE
COMMUNITIES THAT RELY ON SAN FRANCISCO'S ARTS AND NIGHTLIFE
ECONOMY. HE ALSO PLAYED A LEADING ROLE
IN ESTABLISHING THE SAN FRANCISCO ENTERTAINMENT
COMMISSION. HE STRONGLY BELIEVED THE
NIGHTCLUBS AND ENTERTAINMENT ARE A FORM OF FREE SPEECH.
HE ALSO CONTRIBUTED TO LGBTQ PLUS CULTURAL HERITAGE IN THE
CITY. WHEN GILBERT BAKER CREATED THE
ICONIC RAINBOW FLAG IN 1978, HE DID SO IN A STUDIO RENTED FROM
MARK WHO DOCUMENTED THE PROCESS WITH HIS CAMERA.
THE IMAGES WERE LATER SHOWN TO THE SAN FRANCISCO MUSEUM OF
MODERN ART. UNTIL RECENTLY MARK CONTINUE TO
FIGHT FOR THE RIGHTS OF NIGHTCLUB OWNERS AND ARTISTS
THROUGH HIS LAW FIRM NOW GOING ON 51 YEARS.
HE CONTRIBUTED ENORMOUSLY TO SAN FRANCISCO'S UNIQUE CULTURE
AND NIGHTLIFE AND WAS A WELL-KNOWN FIGURE IN THE CITY'S
ENTERTAINMENT COMMUNITY. THERE WILL BE A PUBLIC MEMORIAL
FOR HIM ON NOVEMBER 2ND AT THE CHAPEL AND SO I'M ALSO
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION DESIGNATING THAT DAY MARQUEE
RAINY DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO. I WANT TO THANK AUDREY JOSEPH
AND LIAM SHAI FOR THEIR HELP WITH THE RESOLUTION.
WE SEND OUR CONDOLENCES TO MARK'S FAMILY AND MANY FRIENDS
. REST IN PEACE MARC RENNIE.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING. >> I AM ALSO ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF TERRENCE ALLAN WHO
DIED THIS WEEKEND AT THE AGE OF 73.
TERRENCE ALLAN ATTENDED FENTON HIGH SCHOOL AND BENSENVILLE,
ILLINOIS. HE SPENT A YEAR STUDYING URBAN
PLANNING AT CORNELL COLLEGE, A YEAR STUDYING ART
AND PHILOSOPHY AT ELMHURST COLLEGE AND OTHER YEARS
STUDYING ARCHITECTURE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS AT
CHICAGO AND A YEAR AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN
FRANCISCO WHERE HE LIVED IN A VOLKSWAGEN BUS ON THE OCEAN
WITH HIS TWO DOGS. >> IN THE 90S TERENCE GOT
INVOLVED WITH THE DENNIS PERON'S GAY WEED MAFIA.
TERRENCE WORKED ALONGSIDE PERON AND FELLOW CANNABIS ACTIVIST
BROWNIE MARY TO SUCCESSFULLY PASS PROP 215 IN 1996 WHICH
LEGALIZED MEDICAL MARIJUANA. SHORTLY AFTER PASSAGE HE OPENED
THE NATION'S FIRST NONPROFIT DISPENSARY CHAMP CALIFORNIANS
HELPING TO ALLEVIATE MEDICAL PROBLEMS IN THE 2000.
TERRENCE, A NIGHTCLUB OWNER HIMSELF, BEGAN ADVOCATING FOR
THE CITY'S ENTERTAINMENT INDUSTRY AND HELPED FORM THE
S.F. LATE NIGHT COALITION. HE CAMPAIGNED FOR AND SERVED AS
A FOUNDING MEMBER OF THE ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSION
IN 2009. HE HELPED START THE LOVE PARADE
AND HOW WEIRD STREET FAIR TERRENCE WAS AN ACTIVE MEMBER
OF THE CASTRO COMMUNITY AS WELL.
HIS TENURE ON THE CASTRO MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION LED TO
INSTALLATION OF THE RAINBOW PULL BANNERS ALONG THE
COMMERCIAL CORRIDOR. AND HE FOUGHT TO PROTECT THE
NOW LANDMARKED GILBERT BAKER FLAG.
HIS PUBLIC INVOLVEMENT ALSO INCLUDED SHARING THE S.F.
CANNABIS STATE LEGALIZATION TASK FORCE AND SERVICES, A
BOARD MEMBER ON THE TENDERLOIN EQUITABLE DEVELOPMENT PROJECT.
PRESIDENT OF THE CASTRO EMERGENCIES ASSOCIATION BOARD
MEMBER OF THE CALIFORNIA MUSIC AND CULTURE ASSOCIATION
AND BOARD MEMBER OF THE TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY BENEFIT
DISTRICT. >> JOE CORUBA, A FRIEND OF
TERENCE'S DESCRIBED HIM AS A FORCE OF NATURE KIND, CREATIVE,
RELENTLESS AND UTTERLY DEVOTED TO HIS COMMUNITY.
HE HELPED SHAPE SAN FRANCISCO'S CANNABIS NIGHTLIFE, CANNABIS
NIGHTLIFE AND LGBTQ PLUS CULTURE IN WAYS THAT WILL BE
FELT FOR GENERATIONS. REST IN PEACE AND POWER
TERRANCE ALLAN. MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SUTTER.
>> SUBMIT. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER, THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION
OF NEW BUSINESS. >> WELL, THEN LET'S GO TO
PUBLIC COMMENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
AT THIS TIME IF YOU LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE
CHAMBER WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AND YOU'RE ABLE
YOU'RE ABLE TO SPEAK TO THE MAYORAL APPEARANCE TO THE
MINUTES AS PRESENTED FOR SEPTEMBER 9TH AND SEPTEMBER
16TH. >> ITEMS 50 FOUR THROUGH 58 ON
THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AND OTHER GENERAL
MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT WITHIN THE BOARDS
SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION. ALL RIGHT.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST SPEAKER.
>> WELCOME. WE DON'T WORRY WE DON'T EXPECT
YOU TO ADHERE ON THIS NEW OR FAKE MEETING OF PEDOPHILES
IN THE NAME OF THE THOUSANDS OF CHILDREN BEING SACRIFICED,
MURDERED, TRAFFICKED, RAPED EVERY DAY.
DON'T WORRY. WE DON'T EXPECT THAT FROM YOU.
>> YOU CAN ALWAYS USE A GAVEL ON YOUR HEAD BECAUSE THE DESK
DID NOTHING WRONG TO YOU, MY FRIEND.
THERE IS ONE MISSING. GOOD RIDDANCE.
>> I THINK ACTUALLY, YOU KNOW WE PROBABLY ARE GOING TO NEED
NEW KINGS THAT TAKE CARE OF THE BUSINESS.
>> I DON'T THINK IS THE WAY TO WORLD KINGS BECAUSE WE DON'T
WANT PEDOPHILES ANYMORE IN SOCIETY ANYWHERE.
>> SO WHO IS GOING TO ENFORCE THIS?
I THINK IT'S SOMETHING LIKE A KING OBVIOUSLY NOT THE GUY
IN CHARGE NOW SINCE HE'S A BIG TIME PEDOPHILE.
>> SO WE NEED TO WELCOME THE NATIONAL GUARDS OF PEDOPHILES.
>> I THINK IT'S WHAT'S IN THE AGENDA SOMEHOW.
>> OKAY. I DIDN'T WANT TO COME TODAY
HONESTLY, I'M A BIT SHORT OF INSPIRATION BUT I WISH THERE
WAS MORE GUYS LIKE ME. >> YOU SEE THE PROBLEM IS THAT
THERE ISN'T. >> SO I FOLLOW MY ORDERS FROM
THIS GUYS. I HAVE NO CHOICE.
MY MISSION KEEPS GOING UNTIL YOU GUYS REPENT.
IT'D BE TOUGH. OTHERWISE WHAT IS AWAITING YOU
IS AN INSTITUTION WHERE YOU WON'T GET OUT NO MATTER HOW
LONG IT TAKES. >> I SAID BEFORE NO MATTER HOW
HARD YOU TRY YOU UNINTELLIGENT PEDOPHILES.
>> IT'S GUN GUN. >> IT'S NOT GOING TO WORK.
YOU UNDERSTAND? NEVER.
>> BECAUSE I'M HERE ON 90 9.9. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> CAN WE HEAR FROM THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE?
GOOD NIGHT. THANK YOU.
YOU'RE WELCOME. >> WELCOME.
WELL, READING THE FALL BY ALBERT CAMUS A FRENCH MAN WHO
FIGHTS AGAINST NAZIS DURING WORLD WAR TWO I CAME ACROSS
SOME PASSAGES THAT REMINDED ME OF S.F. POLITICIANS THERE IS A
MAN WHO TARGETS PRIVILEGED FOLKS WHO HAVE LATENT DESIRES
FOR FASCISM OR AT LEAST AN OPENNESS TO FURTHER OPPRESSED
PEOPLE. LET ME SHARE A FEW QUOTES QUOTE
. >> I ANNOUNCED THE PUBLICATION
OF A MANIFESTO EXPOSING THE OPPRESSION THAT THE OPPRESSED
INFLICT ON DECENT PEOPLE. >> ONE DAY WHILE I WAS EATING
LOBSTER AT A SIDEWALK RESTAURANT AND A BEGGAR
BOTHERED ME I CALLED THE PROPRIETOR TO DRIVE HIM AWAY
AND LOUDLY APPROVE THE WORDS OF THAT ADMINISTRATOR OF JUSTICE.
YOU ARE EMBARRASSING PEOPLE, HE SAID.
JUST PUT YOURSELF IN THE PLACE OF THESE LADIES AND GENTS AFTER
ALL, THAT REMINDS ME OF GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS WHO DON'T
KNOW HOW TO EMPATHIZE WITH SUFFERING PEOPLE.
THESE SUFFERING PEOPLE ARE SEEN AS AN IMPEDIMENT
AND EMBARRASSING PROBLEM BUT THEY CAN'T EXPLAIN TO THEIR
KIDS. >> THIS ATTITUDE PUSHES OUR
GOVERNMENTS TO DEPLOY POLICING AND BANISHMENT AS A SOLUTION
INSTEAD OF ACTUAL CARE AND CONSIDERATION.
QUOTE I AM FOR ANY THEORY THAT REFUSES TO GRANT MAN INNOCENCE
AND FOR ANY PRACTICE THAT TREATS HIM AS GUILTY.
YOU SEE IN ME AN ENLIGHTENED ADVOCATES OF SLAVERY.
>> THIS REMINDS ME OF THE BOARD'S APPROACH TO PEOPLE WITH
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER. NO ONE COURTS USING SUBSTANCES
LIKE FENTANYL IS INNOCENT. THEY ARE MARKED AS GUILTY
INSTEAD OF BEING SEEN AS A PERSON EXISTING PROBABLY ALSO
SUFFERING. NO JUDGMENT IS NECESSARY BUT
UNDER ANTI-SCIENCE POLICIES REALLY ANTI HUMANIST POLICIES
OUR GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN IMPLEMENTING.
ABSTINENCE IS SUPREME. THIS CREATES A HIERARCHY AMONG
PEOPLE. THOSE WHO DON'T USE SUBSTANCES
ARE BETTER THAN THOSE THAT DO. THIS HIERARCHY DEVALUES THE
LIVES OF THOSE WHO USE. EVEN IF IT ISN'T VOLUNTARY, IT
DOESN'T MATTER. YOU HAVE CREATED A VALUE SYSTEM
FOR HUMAN LIFE AND PUT PEOPLE WHO CAN ABSTAIN AT THE TOP.
>> QUOTE I INVITE THE GOOD PEOPLE TO SUBMIT TO AUTHORITY
AND HUMBLY SOLICIT THE COMFORTS OF SLAVERY EVEN IF I HAVE TO
PRESENT IT AS TRUE FREEDOM. EVERY EXCUSE FOR INCREASING
POLICE SURVEILLANCE, FOR REDUCING POLICE OVERSIGHT
AND FOR INCREASING THE POLICE BUDGET IS ROOTED IN THAT QUOTE
. >> I KNOW I'M NOT FREE UNDER
MASSIVE INVASIVE SURVEILLANCE AND POLICING.
DO YOU ARE YOU AWARE OF THAT? >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. I HAVE A HANDOUT.
YES. WE'LL COME COLLECT THAT FROM
YOU. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. FOR THE RECORD, MY NAME IS
CHRIS WARD KLEIN. I ALSO GO BY SERGEANT KLEIN OF
THE UNITED STATES MARINE CORPS. I FIRST WANTED TO ASK FOR YOUR
SUPPORT TO GET WITH THE SHERIFF AND THE POLICE CHIEF TO MOVE
FORWARD WITH THE INVESTIGATION. A REPORT THAT WAS FILED AND WE
WILL BE SUBMITTING THAT FINAL REPORT NOVEMBER 14TH TO THE
SHERIFF'S OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE. SO WE ARE TRYING TO PUT
PRESSURE ON THE SHERIFF TO MOVE FORWARD WITH THIS.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT AND I JUST HANDED OUT A SHEET HERE.
JUST PAY ATTENTION TO THE LAST PART.
THERE'S A UNIVERSITY THAT HAS PUT LARGE NUMBERS OF PEOPLE
IN SAN FRANCISCO ON SURVEILLANCE AND THEY'VE DONE
IT BEFORE. NOW WE ARE ASKING FOR THEM TO
TURN OFF THEIR SURVEILLANCE OF PRIMARILY LGBTQ PLUS MEMBERS
BUT ALSO AFRICAN-AMERICANS. YOU'LL SEE THE NAME HERE.
I'M NOT GOING TO READ IT OUT PUBLICLY BUT PLEASE LOOK AT IT.
PLEASE CALL THAT UNIVERSITY. PLEASE HAVE THEM STOP THEIR
SURVEILLANCE. BASICALLY THE MILITARY HAS
ALREADY CALLED THEM AND I SAID STOP WORK IMMEDIATELY.
THAT MEANS THAT IF THE MILITARY DOES COME IN AND THEY DO NOT
STOP WORK, THE MILITARY WILL COME IN AND CONFISCATE THEIR
EQUIPMENT. IT IS A SERIOUS ISSUE.
LISTENING TO SOME OF YOUR STORIES, YOU PROBABLY WERE
IMPACTED WITH YOUR JOURNEYS BY THIS UNIVERSITY SO PLEASE TAKE
A LOOK AT IT. PLEASE ACT ON IT.
AND AGAIN I'M ASKING FOR YOUR SUPPORT AND TALKING TO SHERIFF
PAUL MIYAMOTO AND THE INTERIM POLICE CHIEF PAUL YAP
AND MOVING FORWARD WITH THE INVESTIGATION THAT WAS TURNED
OVER TO THEIR OFFICERS. I'M NOT GOING TO NAME THE
PEOPLE IN THAT REPORT. I THINK THERE WAS A COPY THAT
WAS HAND-DELIVERED TO THIS BOARD.
I'M IT IS VERY SERIOUS AND IT NEEDS TO STOP IMMEDIATELY.
AND AS OF RIGHT NOW THERE'S A 97% CHANCE THE MILITARY IS
COMING IN. THAT'S BECAUSE THESE
UNIVERSITIES WILL NOT TURN OFF THEIR EQUIPMENT AND THEY GET
FUNDING FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE AND THE COMMERCE
DEPARTMENT. SO IF THEY COME IN THAT IS THE
REASON THAT THEY HAVE TO COME IN.
IT'S NOT BECAUSE OF ANYTHING ELSE.
IT'S NOT BECAUSE OF POLITICS. IT'S BECAUSE THEY WON'T TURN
OFF THE EQUIPMENT THAT THEY HAVE TURNED ON ILLEGALLY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE. HELLO SUPERVISORS.
THEY I AM A MEMBER OF THE SAN FRANCISCO QUAKER MEETING.
I'M HERE TO ADDRESS AN ISSUE THAT I KNOW MATTERS AND IS ON
THE HEART OF MANY PEOPLE HERE WHICH IS CULTURAL COMPETENCY
ACROSS OUR PROVIDER SECTOR FOR THOSE THAT ARE PROVIDING
SERVICES FOR THE UNHOUSED. WE LAUNCHED A MINISTRY WITH
GLIDE WHEREBY WE ACCOMPANY PEOPLE, MEET THEM WHERE THEY
ARE AND TRY TO UNDERSTAND WHAT THEIR LIFE NARRATIVE IS SO THAT
WE CAN BETTER IMPACT THEIR OUTCOMES.
>> I JUST WANT TO SHARE WITH YOU THAT I WAS VERY
DISAPPOINTED BY AN EXPERIENCE WE HAD RECENTLY ACCOMPANYING
SOMEONE THAT WE TRIED TO OVERCOME EVERY BARRIER THAT
THEY HAD AND THE PROVIDER COULDN'T HAVE GONE MORE OUT OF
THEIR WAY TO MAKE THE PERSON MORE REACTIVE, MORE ESCALATED,
FEEL LESS WARRANTED. THE PROVIDER FELT DISTANT.
THEY WERE ROLLING THEIR EYES. THEIR BODY LANGUAGE WAS CLOSED
OFF. THEY LITERALLY COULDN'T HAVE
DONE A BETTER JOB TO TURN THIS PERSON AWAY FROM SERVICES.
ONE OF THE CHALLENGES THAT WE HAVE IS THAT NONE OF THE DATA
CAPTURES THE PATIENT ADVOCACY SIDE UNLESS A NEGATIVE
EXPERIENCE TRIGGERS A REPORT. WE CANNOT EXPECT REPORTS FROM
PEOPLE WHO ARE IN ACTIVE PSYCHIATRIC CRISIS.
>> SO IN THE SAME WAYS THAT WE STAFF WITH SECURITY PERSONNEL
IT MIGHT BE THAT WE NEED TO STAFF SOME SITE, SOME PILOT
PROJECTS WITH PATIENT ADVOCATES THAT REPORT LACK OF CULTURAL
COMPETENCY BECAUSE PROVIDERS ARE NOT GOING TO BE IN THE
BUSINESS OF SELF-REPORTING A LACK OF CULTURAL COMPETENCY.
I KNOW THAT WE ALL CARE ABOUT GETTING PEOPLE TOWARDS THEIR
OUTCOMES AND I KNOW THAT WE ALL CARE ABOUT MAKING SAN FRANCISCO
A BETTER CITY. AND TO THE EARLIER SPEAKER I
JUST PUBLISHED A BOOK A COUPLE OF MONTHS AGO AND THE LAST FEW
LINES OF UAP NEWTON'S AUTOBIOGRAPHY REVOLUTIONARY
SUICIDE ARE A QUOTE FROM CAMPBELL.
AND I KNOW THAT'S WHAT WE'RE ALL HERE TO DO, WHICH IS TO
REMAKE THE SOUL OF OUR TIME. >> BLESS YOU ALL.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
ON SUPER BOWL MONDAY RORY GAMBRELL.
I LIVE IN A LEVEL 90 MISSION STREET.
>> I'M HERE TODAY TO DEFEAT THE PROBLEM I'M HAVING AT MY PLACE.
MY LIFE WAS OFFICE SEVEN DAYS AND SEVEN NIGHTS I'M DUE TO MY
LANDLORD AND I GOT INJURED INSIDE OF MY ROOM.
I HAVE A HEAD INJURY RIGHT NOW AS WE SPEAK DUE TO THE FORTUNE
OF MY LANDLORD AND RIGHT NOW THAT I HAD COMPLAINED TO H S H
ABOUT MY HEAD INJURY HE DIDN'T DO ANYTHING.
I WAS RELEASED FROM THE HOSPITAL FOR MY HEAD INJURY
AND TO THE PUMP. THE PRESIDENT OF THE NWC THE
HOSPITAL CALL HIM AND RELEASED ME INTO HIS CUSTODY BECAUSE OF
THE MY UNIT SITUATION. MY LANDLORD HAS THE POWER TO
TURN MY LIFE BACK ON ANY TIME HE GET READY.
HE STAYED THERE, PUT OFF FOR SEVEN DAYS AND SEVEN NIGHTS
AFTER THE PRESIDENT OF THE NWC PUT IN A WORK ORDER DAY
VIOLATED ME THREE VIOLATIONS I'M ONLY POSSIBLE LOSE MY HOUSE
RIGHT NOW. H S H IS RIGHT NOW DISGUSTING
WHAT THEY'RE GOING TO DO ABOUT MY SITUATION.
THIS IS A GLIB ONE. CASE MANAGER WENT TO H INSISTED
I THREATEN THEM. THEY TOOK THAT INTO
CONSIDERATION BUT THEY ARE NOT TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION ABOUT
MY INJURIES. THIS IS MY SECOND TIME
COMPLAINING ABOUT A STAFF MEMBER.
I WAS HERE IN 2002 WHEN I GOT USED TO BOSS JUST JUST OVER MY
RIGHT EYE AND I HAD TEN STITCHES ALL MY HAIR WHEN I
CAME IN HE HAD HIS PLAYING JUST TO THE LAST PRESIDENT.
SO I'M ASKING Y'ALL THIS TIME I HAVE A PATIENT IN MY HEAD
AND IT COMES FROM NEGLIGENCE OF THE PROPERTY MANAGER AND I GOT
DOCUMENTS AND PICTURES I WANT TO KNOW AND I WANTED TO
DOCUMENT IT. >> I NEED A FINE HOW CAN I GET
IMMEDIATE ATTENTION IMMEDIATE ACTION BECAUSE THEY ARE RIGHT
NOW TRYING TO PUT ME UP. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
THANK YOU. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME.
>> OKAY BYE. YOU'RE OUT OF ORDER MR. FEW
LIKE SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME SIR.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS MY NAME IS OFF FRUIT I'M A
RESIDENT OF DISTRICT NINE. I'M SPEAKING TODAY IN STRONG
SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S GREEN BANK RESOLUTION
AND MOVING FORWARD WITH WHAT SAN FRANCISCO'S PUBLIC BANK.
THE CITY HAS ALREADY SHOWN UNANIMOUS SUPPORT FOR PUBLIC
BANK IN THE PAST BECAUSE IT REFLECTS SAN FRANCISCO'S SHARED
VALUES INVESTING IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING, SMALL BUSINESSES
AND GREEN ENERGY INSTEAD OF LETTING OUR MONEY BE SIPHONED
OFF TO WALL STREET RIGHT NOW WITH THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
SHOWING ACTIVE HOSTILITY TOWARD CLIMATE ACTION, IT'S UP TO
CITIES LIKE OURS TO TAKE THE LEAD.
A PUBLIC AND GREEN BANK WOULD LET US FINANCE RENEWABLE
ENERGY, SOCIAL HOUSING AND LOCAL ENTERPRISE DIRECTLY
KEEPING WEALTH CIRCULATING IN OUR ECONOMY AND LOWERING
COSTS FOR EVERYONE. >> THIS ISN'T A RADICAL IDEA
PUBLIC BANKS ALREADY HOLD 25% OF THE WORLD'S ASSETS THEY WORK
AND HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO THE PUBLIC MANDATE COULDN'T BE
CLEARER. OUR SUPERVISOR FAILED TO
MENTION RECENT POLLING SHOWS THAT NEARLY TWO THIRDS OF
LIKELY VOTERS SUPPORT A PUBLIC BANK AND EVEN MORE IF IT'S A
GREEN BANK. >> THIS IS OUR CHANCE TO BUILD
A SELF-SUSTAINING PUBLIC INSTITUTION THAT DRIVES
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF LOW COST LOANS EVERY YEAR AN
ECONOMIC ENGINE FOR A CITY THAT WORKS FOR EVERYONE NOT JUST THE
WEALTHY. >> LET'S BANK THE BOOM THAT'S
HAPPENING RIGHT NOW IN SAN FRANCISCO AND MAKE SURE THAT IT
BENEFITS WORKING PEOPLE AND OUR PLANET.
>> PLEASE SUPPORT THE GREEN BANK RESOLUTION AND MOVE
FORWARD MOVE FORWARD ON A PUBLIC BANK.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD GOOD TO SEE YOU ALL HERE
TODAY WE CONNECT WITH S.F. DISTRICT TWO RESIDENT HERE FOR
A COUPLE OF REASONS. >> ONE IS URGING SUPERVISOR
FIELDER TO SERVE OUR CONSTITUENTS SERVED WITH
ADDRESSED THE MEMBERS AS A AS THE BODY AS A WHOLE AND NOT AN
INDIVIDUAL SUPERVISOR. THANK YOU SO SO THAT AGAIN YOU
MAY NOT IN MONISH A SINGLE SUPERVISOR PLEASE ADDRESS HIM
AS A FULL BOARD. OKAY LET ME START OVER GRIFFIN
LEE HERE WITH CONNECT WITH S.F. ALSO DISTRICT TWO RESIDENT I'M
HERE TODAY FOR TWO REASONS ONE TO ENCOURAGE SUPERVISOR FOR THE
OTHER TO PAY ATTENTION TO OUR CONSTITUENTS AND ACTUALLY TRY
AND MAKE AN EFFORT TO SOLVE THE PROSTITUTION PROBLEM GOING
ALONG. SHOTWELL THIS IS COMING
DIRECTLY FROM OUR MEMBERS AND WE'VE HEARD THAT YOU HAVE
BEEN UNRESPONSIVE TO THIS SITUATION AND NOPE MADE NO
EFFORT TO TRY AND DISSOLVE THIS SITUATION.
>> IT'S A PUBLIC SAFETY ISSUE SO I THINK THAT'S WHY WE SHOULD
STOP THAT TIME. >> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, WE
HAVE BOARD RULES AND THEY SAY FOLKS ARE NOT SUPPOSED TO
ADDRESS MEMBERS OF THE BOARD INDIVIDUALLY.
>> IS THAT CORRECT? >> YES.
SORRY I HAVE DURING ITS BATTERING I DID NOT TRY
AND DEFY THE RULES THERE, TRY ADDRESS, TRY TO AT LEAST STATE
OR LET'S GO BACK TO OUR ONE MINUTE AND 30S AND ALL RIGHT
HOW DO I GO ABOUT THIS TO THE BOARD?
>> I HOPE YOU TRY AND ACTUALLY SOLVE THE MATTER AND COORDINATE
WITH DIFFERENT AGENCIES AS A PD PUBLIC WORKS WHOEVER ELSE MAY
BE INVOLVED TO COMBAT THE PROSTITUTION PROBLEM ON
SHOTWELL I'VE HEARD FROM THERE ARE SOME MEMBERS OF OUR MEMBERS
THAT CONNECT TO SERVE THAT THE PROBLEM IS STILL A PROBLEM.
>> SECONDLY, I WOULD LIKE TO THANK RAFAEL.
SUPERVISOR MATHEMATICS OR FROM HIS DORSEY FOR THEIR ACTION
IN RESPONSE TO AB 255I HAVE A SPECIFIC AMENDMENT THAT I
WANTED TO ADDRESS AND HOPEFULLY YOU TO CONSIDER AND THAT IS AN
ORDINANCE AMENDING THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO STAY
IN THE CITY POLICY TO EXPAND THE AVAILABILITY OF THE BOARD
PERMANENT SUPPORT OF OUT EXCUSE ME BASED SITE BASED PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING FOR PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS WHO
HAVE FORMERLY LIVED IN SAN FRANCISCO BY PROOF OF PAST
RESIDENCE THE HOME ADDRESS NOT INCLUDING AN INDIVIDUAL WHO
FALLS WHO FAILS TO SHOW PROOF OF PAST RESIDENCE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> FURTHERMORE INDIVIDUAL HAS A
PCH ADDRESS IN SAN FRANCISCO IN THE PAST THAT SUPPORTS
ABSTINENCE BY PROHIBIT. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
YOUR TWO MINUTES IS EXPIRED. NEXT SPEAKER HELLO SUPERVISORS
. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS SCOTT FEENEY. I'M A RESIDENT OF THE MISSION
DISTRICT AND I'M CALLING AND COMMITTING TO ASK FOR ALL
OF YOUR SUPPORT FOR SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S RESOLUTION TOWARDS A
PUBLICLY OWNED GREEN BANK WITH THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION
SLASHING FUNDING FOR CLIMATE ACTION, WE NEED TO ACT LOCALLY
MORE THAN EVER. A PUBLIC BANK WILL PROVIDE THE
ABILITY TO DO THAT MORE AFFORDABLY AS WELL AS PROVIDING
MORE AFFORDABLE FUNDING FOR IMPORTANT TRANSIT
INFRASTRUCTURE AND FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO MAKE THAT
YOU KNOW, THAT CONTROVERSIAL ZONING PLAN THAT WE'VE BEEN
TALKING ABOUT MAKE THAT WORK FOR THE 46,000 LOW AND MIDDLE
INCOME AFFORDABLE UNITS THAT WE NEED A GREEN BANK WILL BE A WAY
TO FUND ALL OF THESE THINGS AND MORE.
SO I HOPE THAT YOU ALL SUPPORT IT AND I APPRECIATE THOSE OF
YOU WHO'VE ALREADY SIGNED ON AS CO-SPONSORS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER HI, MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS I'M ON
YOUR WALL-E ZIGMUND WITH THE PEOPLE'S BUDGET COALITION.
I THANK EACH OF YOU WHO CAME OUT TO DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
AWARENESS MONTH TODAY AND I WANTED TO EMPHASIZE SORT OF THE
LINE OF PEOPLE'S BUDGET AND REMINDING YOU THAT A FULLY
FUNDED PUBLIC SAFETY SYSTEM REALLY MEANS INVESTING IN OUR
LOCAL PROVIDERS WITH THAT CULTURAL COMPETENCY IS REALLY,
REALLY VITAL. AND I WANT TO REMIND YOU FOLKS
THAT LAST YEAR S.F. PD'S OVERTIME COULD HAVE MORE THAN
14 TIMES PAID FOR OUR TOTAL DOMESTIC VIOLENCE INVESTMENT AS
A CITY. JUST THEIR OVERTIME COULD HAVE
PAID FOR MORE THAN 14 TIMES. SO WHEN WE TALK ABOUT A FULLY
FUNDED PUBLIC SAFETY SYSTEM, WE HAVE TO BE REAL ABOUT WHERE
WE'RE STARTING FROM AND BUILD ON TOP OF THAT IN MY PERSONAL
CAPACITY I'M ALSO HERE TO SUPPORT THE PUBLIC BANK
RESOLUTION AS WELL. IN THESE TIMES WE NEED TO BE
REALLY CREATIVE ABOUT RAISING FUNDING AND LOOKING AT HOW WE
AS SAN FRANCISCO CAN INSTITUTIONALIZE OUR OWN WEALTH
HERE AND REDISTRIBUTE IT. WE CAN'T RELY ON THE STATE OR
ON THE FEDERAL INFRASTRUCTURE TO HELP KEEP US SAFE AND SAN
FRANCISCO WE HAVE A BEAUTIFUL CITY HERE THAT WE NEED TO
PROTECT AND DOUBLE DOWN ON AS BEST WE CAN.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
HONORABLE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. MY NAME IS JUSTIN LOCKE.
I AM THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF NOT IN OUR TOWN.
I WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU ALL TODAY FOR CONSIDERING THE
RESOLUTION LATER IN TODAY'S AGENDA COMMEMORATING UNITED
AGAINST HATE WEEK FOR 30 YEARS NOT IN OUR TOWN HAS HELPED
COMMUNITIES STAND UP TO HATE WITH LOCAL LEADERSHIP AT THE
CENTER UNITE AGAINST HATE WE BEGAN AS A BAY AREA EFFORT
AND HAS SINCE GROWN FROM JUST 13 COMMUNITIES IN 2018 TO MORE
THAN 200 PARTICIPATING SCHOOL DISTRICTS, COMMUNITY
ORGANIZATIONS, TOWNS, CITIES AND CIVIC ENTITIES ACROSS THE
COUNTRY. SAN FRANCISCO'S VOICE CARRIES
FAR WHEN YOU LEAD, OTHERS LISTEN AND OTHERS FOLLOW.
THIS RESOLUTION MATTERS BECAUSE IT DOES MORE THAN MARK A WEEK
ON THE CALENDAR. IT SIGNALS THAT SAN FRANCISCO
STANDS SHOULDER TO SHOULDER WITH NEIGHBORS WHO HAVE BEEN
TARGETS OF HATE WHETHER THEY BE THE AAPI, BLACK, LATINO, JEWISH
,MUSLIM, ARAB, SICK, LGBTQ PLUS OR DISABLED COMMUNITIES OR
ANY OF THE OTHER COMMUNITIES WHO ARE THREATENED BY BIGOTRY
AND VIOLENCE. >> IT INVITES EVERY DISTRICT TO
TAKE ACTION SCHOOLS TO HOST DIALOGS, LIBRARIES TO SHARE
LEARNING RESOURCES, SMALL BUSINESSES TO POST SOLIDARITY
SIGNS CITY AGENCIES TO PROMOTE REPORTING CHANNELS AND VICTIM
SUPPORT AND NEIGHBORHOOD GROUPS TO ORGANIZE UNITY WALKS, ART
BUILDS BI CENTER AND UPSTANDER TRAININGS OR OTHER GRASSROOTS
EFFORTS TO COUNTERACT HATE IN ALL ITS FORMS IF ADOPTED NOT
IN OUR TOWN IS COMMITTED TO CONTINUING TO PARTNER WITH YOUR
OFFICES TO PROVIDE TOOLKITS, FILM AND DISCUSSION GUIDES
AND CONNECTIONS TO COMMUNITY LEADERS SO THAT EVERY DISTRICT
CAN ACTIVATE QUICKLY. WE KNOW THAT WHEN CITIES
COORDINATE PUBLIC SAFETY SCHOOLS, ARTS, ARTSPACE
AND COMMUNITY GROUPS PEOPLE FEEL SAFER, MORE SEEN AND MORE
WILLING TO SPEAK UP FOR ONE ANOTHER.
THANK YOU FOR ELEVATING THIS WORK AND FOR MODELING WHAT
CIVIC COURAGE LOOKS LIKE. UNITE AGAINST HATE DOES NOT END
AFTER THESE SEVEN DAYS. IT STRENGTHENS EVERYDAY FABRIC
OF THE CITY. WE ARE GRATEFUL FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP AND STAND READY TO HELP SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS RICK GIRLING. I'M A MEMBER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC BANK COALITION AND THE CALIFORNIA PUBLIC
BANKING ALLIANCE. >> I'VE LIVED IN SAN FRANCISCO
FOR 50 YEARS. I'VE SEEN A LOT OF CHANGES,
SOME GOOD AND SOME NOT SO GOOD. A LOT NOT SO GOOD ACTUALLY.
>> I RETIRED FROM TEACHING IN SAN FRANCISCO UNIFIED SCHOOL
DISTRICT AFTER 30 YEARS IN 2017.
AT THAT TIME I JOINED WITH A NUMBER OF OTHER FOLKS WHO WERE
INTERESTED IN GETTING SOMETHING DONE TO START A PUBLIC BANK
IN SAN FRANCISCO. I'VE BEEN TO SACRAMENTO.
I'VE BEEN TO MEETINGS WITH THE TASK FORCE.
I'VE BEEN TO EVERY MEETING YOU COULD POSSIBLY IMAGINE
AND TALKED WITH MANY, MANY PEOPLE ABOUT THIS.
I HAVEN'T COME ACROSS ANYONE WHO'S AGAINST SETTING UP A
PUBLIC BANK EXCEPT FOR THE BANKERS.
YOU KNOW, THE FEW BANKERS THAT DON'T LIKE IT.
AND I DON'T UNDERSTAND WHY IT'S TAKEN US SO LONG TO DO
SOMETHING SO SIMPLE. IT'S REALLY YOU KNOW AND GIVEN
THE CURRENT SITUATION WHERE WE ARE UNDER SIEGE FROM A
GOVERNMENT IN WASHINGTON DC, WE NEED TO TAKE THINGS IN OUR OWN
HANDS AND THIS IS ONE THING WE CAN EASILY DO.
AND I WOULD ENCOURAGE YOU TO DO ALL THE THINGS THAT YOU CAN
POSSIBLY DO TO MAKE THIS HAPPEN AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE.
WE TRANSITION TO MAKE IT A GREEN BANK BECAUSE WE THOUGHT
THAT WOULD MAKE IT EASIER AND QUICKER AND IT SHOULD BE
EASIER AND QUICKER AND I WOULD ENCOURAGE YOU TO REALLY DO
EVERYTHING YOU COULD POSSIBLY DO TO SUPPORT THE RESOLUTION TO
GET THIS GREEN BANK GOING. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS MISCHA STYER.
AND DISTRICT SEVEN RESIDENT AND LEAD ORGANIZER FOR THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC BANK COALITION.
I'M HERE TO SPEAK IN STRONG SUPPORT OF THE RESOLUTION TO
EXPLORE AND PURSUE FUNDING FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A GREEN
BANK. THE CITY'S WORK TO DATE ON THE
PUBLIC BANK IN GREEN BANK HAS BEEN A REALLY INSPIRING EXAMPLE
OF UNIVERSALLY SHARED VALUES. AND IT HAS BEEN SUPPORTED BY
POLICYMAKERS UNANIMOUSLY ENJOYING UNANIMOUS VOTES AT THE
BOARD. WHENEVER THE OPPORTUNITY HAS
ARISEN THIS RESOLUTION IS AN OPPORTUNITY TO CONTINUE THIS
EXPRESSION OF UNIVERSAL SAN FRANCISCO VALUES SUPPORTING
AFFORDABLE HOUSING, SMALL BUSINESS AND GREEN ENERGY.
THIS BOARD THIS BROAD SUPPORT CAN BE ATTRIBUTED TO THE CLEAR
BENEFITS FOR SAN FRANCISCO. REGARDLESS OF YOUR IDEOLOGY WE
ALL CARE ABOUT WHAT'S IN SAN FRANCISCO'S BEST INTERESTS
AND THE BENEFITS OF A GREEN BANK ARE CLEAR.
A GREEN BANK IS AN ECONOMIC ENGINE FOR A CITY THAT WORKS
FOR EVERYONE. ISSUING AND RECYCLING MILLIONS
OF LOANS EACH AND EVERY YEAR IN LOW COST LOANS FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING, GREEN ENERGY AND SMALL BUSINESS.
I ENCOURAGE YOU TO SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION AND SEE THROUGH THIS
GROUNDBREAKING WORK THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS DECLARED WAR
AND IN FACT ON ANY EFFORTS TO ADDRESS CLIMATE CHANGE.
AND IT IS ALL THE MORE ESSENTIAL THAT SAN FRANCISCO
REITERATE OUR COMMITMENT TO COMBATING CLIMATE CHANGE LOUDLY
AND WHENEVER POSSIBLE. THIS RESOLUTION IS AN
OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL OF US TO COME TOGETHER AND DECLARE OUR
COMMITMENT TO COMBATING CLIMATE CHANGE.
THERE ARE MYRIAD BENEFITS FOR A GREEN BANK.
THE COST OF LIVING IS AN ISSUE TOP OF EVERYONE'S MIND.
WE ARE SEEING SKYROCKETING RENTS.
WE ARE SEEING ENERGY PRICES SPIKING AND WE ARE SEEING SMALL
BUSINESSES BEING DISPLACED AND FORCED TO RAISE THEIR
PRICES. >> THE SUPPORT THAT A GREEN
BANK CAN PROVIDE WILL HELP LOWER COST IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND AS HAS BEEN MENTIONED, POLLING HAS BEEN CONDUCTED
RECENTLY INDICATING WHAT I LIKELY SUSPECT MANY OF YOU KNOW
GIVEN YOUR SUPPORT FOR THE GREEN BANK IN THE PAST AND THE
PUBLIC BANK IN THE PAST THAT THIS IS A VERY POPULAR IDEA
IN SAN FRANCISCO TWO THIRDS OF LIKELY VOTERS SUPPORT A PUBLIC
BANK. 70% OF THOSE VOTERS SUPPORT
STARTING A PUBLIC BANK AS A GREEN BANK.
SO THIS IS A FANTASTIC OPPORTUNITY TO CONTINUE THIS
GROUNDBREAKING WORK. >> YOU'LL BE THE FIRST CITY
IN THE COUNTRY WITH A MUNICIPAL PUBLIC BANK.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS SYLVIA CHEE.
I AM ALSO HERE TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE GREEN BANK
RESOLUTION. >> I'M ALSO A MEMBER OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC BANKING COALITION AND THE CALIFORNIA
PUBLIC BANKING ALLIANCE AND I ALSO SERVED ON THE CITY'S
REINVESTMENT WORKING GROUP. AND I WANTED TO HIGHLIGHT THAT
EXPERIENCE. >> AS YOU KNOW, THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AUTHORIZED THAT WORKING GROUP AND WE MET FOR
MONTHS AND MONTHS AND DEVELOPED DETAILED PLANS FEASIBILITY
PLANS FOR BOTH THE GREEN BANK AND THE PUBLIC BANK AS AN
INSTITUTION. SO WE'VE PROVEN THAT IT'S
DOABLE. >> AS MISCHA JUST MENTIONED, IT
IS ALSO POPULAR AMONG SAN FRANCISCO CONSTITUENTS.
AND AS OTHER COMMENTERS HAVE ALL HIGHLIGHTED, IT'S VERY
CRITICAL IN THIS MOMENT WHEN WE'RE FACING THESE CHALLENGES
WITH FEDERAL FUNDING AS I'M SURE YOU ALL KNOW, THE CURRENT
FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION IS CHOKING OFF FUNDING TO THE CITY
NOT JUST IN TERMS OF FUNDS DIRECTLY TO THE CITY BUT ALSO
THROUGH THE STATE AND AS WELL AS OTHER INTERMEDIARIES LIKE
CODIFIES COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS.
AND AS OTHERS HAVE NOTED, THEIR ATTACKS ON CLIMATE ACTION HAVE
BEEN REALLY DEVASTATING. BUT THEY'VE ALSO BEEN ATTACKING
OTHER IMPORTANT SAN FRANCISCO VALUES INCLUDING RACIAL
JUSTICE, SMALL BUSINESSES AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THEY JUST LAID OFF THE ENTIRE STAFF OF THE FIVE FUND.
THEY'VE ATTACKED HUD. SO ALL OF THESE ARE AREAS THAT
CAN BE MITIGATED WITH THE THE GREEN BANK INDIVIDUAL SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC BANK. ONE OTHER NOTE IS THAT THE
CITY'S CLIMATE ACTION PLAN HAS NO WAY TO BE FUNDED AT THIS
MOMENT. THE BERKELEY CENTER FOR LAW,
ENERGY AND ENVIRONMENT HAS IDENTIFIED A GREEN BANK A
MUNICIPAL GREEN BANK BANK AS A WAY TO PAY FOR IT.
>> SO I ENCOURAGE YOU ALL TO SUPPORT THE RESOLUTION.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HELLO, I'M ENGINEER AMY. >> NOW MY STAY OR THE PUBLIC
NOW MUST STAY FOR THE PUBLIC A HARDSHIP COM NINE NOW MY STAND
HEARTFELT HAPPY THE VALLEY MADE THIS FESTIVAL OF LIGHT BRING
JOY PEACE AND PROSPERITY TO ALL IN OUR VIBRANT SAN FRANCISCO
AND PROTECT US ALL IN THESE TIMES.
MIGNINI HAD THE PICTURE OR SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISOR K
SARDAR SARDAR CAN YOU SOME MONEY TO THAT CAN YOU PROVIDE
GOSSIP GUY J IN ENGLISH NEAR PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ON BEHALF OF THE
PARIVAR BAY AREA ON ALL OF THE INDIAN AND SOUTH ASIAN
COMMUNITIES OF SAN FRANCISCO I RESPECTFULLY REQUEST THE BOARD
TO CONSIDER AND PASS A RESOLUTION CELEBRATING DIWALI
DAY ON OCTOBER 20TH, 2025 IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THIS HISTORIC RESOLUTION THE FIRST INTRODUCED BY PRESIDENT
MADELINE HONORS ONE OF THE WORLD'S MOST CHERISHED
FESTIVALS DIWALI, ALSO KNOWN AS DEEPAVALI DEEPAVALI THE HEART
BAND TOWARD DIVERSE AND KARTIK POORNIMA IT'S ONE OF THE MOST
SACRED AND JOYOUS FESTIVALS CELEBRATED BY HINDUS, SIKHS,
JAINS AND BUDDHISTS AND OTHERS ALIKE.
IT SYMBOLIZES THE TRIUMPH OF LIGHT OVER DARKNESS, HOPE OVER
DESPAIR AND KNOWLEDGE OVER IGNORANCE ALONG WITH NEW
BEGINNINGS LIKE THE GRAND OPENING OF PARTY WHERE BAY
AREA'S OWN COMMUNITY SPACE AND DEFILED LAST NIGHT.
THIS IS ABOUT PEACE, PROSPERITY ,UNITY AND CULTURAL RENEWAL.
AND ON BEHALF OF THE SAN FRANCISCO SOUTH-ASIAN IMMIGRANT
AND ALL OF THE PARIVAR AND THE FAMILIES AND ALL THOSE WHO CALL
SAN FRANCISCO HOME, WE'RE VERY GRATEFUL FOR THE CITY'S
CONTINUED COMMITMENT TO BUILD AWARENESS AND BELONGING TO MANY
OF US IN MANY DIASPORAS AND FURTHERING MULTICULTURAL
CELEBRATIONS. >> JELANI THANK YOU, DANNY, BUT
THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT BIG. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS
BEVERLY UPTON, SAN FRANCISCO DOMESTIC VIOLENCE CONSORTIUM.
IT WAS SO WONDERFUL TO STAND ON THE STEPS OF CITY HALL WITH YOU
TODAY AS WE ARE WAITING FOR A RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE OCTOBER
AS DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AWARENESS MONTH IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. WHEN WE HEARD FROM JULIA TIM
PONGO TODAY AND WE TALKED ABOUT HER SISTER CLAIRE JOYCE, TIM
PONGO WHO WILL BE GONE TAKEN FROM US BY AN ABUSIVE PARTNER
25 YEARS AGO TOMORROW. I THINK WE ALL REMEMBER
AND RECOGNIZE WHAT DOMESTIC VIOLENCE CAN DO TO OUR CITY, TO
OUR COMMUNITIES AND TO THE FAMILIES.
THEY WILL ALWAYS FEEL THAT MANY OF US WILL ALWAYS FEEL THAT.
>> BUT SAN FRANCISCO CAME TOGETHER AND ISSUED THE JUSTICE
AND COURAGE REPORT 400 RECOMMENDATIONS THAT WE ARE
STILL WORKING ON CURRENTLY. AND OF COURSE THERE ARE NEW
ONES. THE FAMILY VIOLENCE COUNCIL.
ALL OF US THE SHELTERS, THE CRISIS LINE LEGAL SERVICES
AND THE BELOVED COMMUNITY, THE COO OF THE CAMERON HOUSES THE
APA FAMILY SERVICES ARE WORKING EVERY DAY TO PROTECT FAMILIES.
>> WE USED TO HAVE 10 TO 12 HOMICIDES A YEAR IN SAN
FRANCISCO. AND NOW IF WE HAVE 1 OR 2 AS WE
SHOULD, WE ARE STILL IN SHOCK. >> BUT IT IS PROGRESS.
>> BUT TO CONTINUE THAT PROGRESS WE'RE REALLY GOING TO
NEED YOUR HELP. >> IMMIGRANT FAMILIES ARE GOING
TO STOP LOOKING FOR SERVICES. WE'RE SO WORRIED ABOUT THIS.
WE'RE WORRIED THAT WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE THE BUDGET TO
KEEP THE SHELTERS OPEN, KEEP THE CRISIS LINES ANSWERED
AND KEEP THE LEGAL SERVICES AND THE CIVIL LEGAL THAT HASN'T
EVEN BEEN STARTED YET THAT THE VOTERS PASSED.
SO WE ARE GOING TO HAVE TO HAVE AN ALL HANDS ON DECK RESPONSE.
>> THAT'S WHAT GOT SAN FRANCISCO TO A 90 SOME ODD
PERCENT REDUCTION IN DOMESTIC VIOLENCE HOMICIDES.
>> BUT IT'S NOT JUST HOMICIDES. WE HAVE TO STOP THE DOMESTIC
VIOLENCE BEFORE IT GETS THERE. >> AND TO DO THAT WE ARE GOING
TO NEED EVERYBODY ALL THE SHELTERS, ALL THE CRISIS LINES.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND SAN
FRANCISCO MAYOR OFFICE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
TODAY'S SPEECH AS TONY ROBBINS PSYCHOLOGICAL SHIFT IN THE YEAR
2007 I WOKE UP WITH A GRANDIOSE IDEA TO BECOME A STAGE
PERFORMER AND A SINGER. IN 2012, AFTER COMPLETING MY
FOUR YEAR STINT IN SIX FLAGS, VALLEJO I WAS PUBLIC RELATIONS
OFFICER OF SIX FLAGS AND I DEBUT SINGING.
I WAS CENTER STAGE OF DISCOVERY KINGDOM IN TWO THOUSAND 15.
>> I HAD KNEE INJURY ON A BUS. >> I BROKE DOWN AND CRIED.
SOMEONE ETCHED AN IDEA THAT I WAS TOO OLD TO BE FRIEND OF A
19 YEAR OLD GIRL NAMED MAGGIE WONG.
IN 2018 SHE'S CROWNED MISS CHINATOWN OR SAN CISCO AND IN
2019 SHE WAS CROWNED MISS POPULAR MISS CHINESE
INTERNATIONAL OF OUR BY TVB AND LOUISA MAC IN 2018.
I'M MET A GIRL THIS THAI GIRL I TEXTED HER WITH FULL
DISAPPOINTMENT THAT SHE'S BACK IN THAILAND TO TAKE CARE OF
MOM. THREE HOURS LATER MAGGIE SAID
SHE'S COMPETING FOR MISS CHINESE INTERNATIONAL.
>> SO IN TWO THOUSAND 2020 THREE I'M BRAND AT TWITTER
MASTER OF X. YES.
I'M THE MAN BEHIND DOGE DEPARTMENT OF DEMOCRATIC
SUPERIORITY IN 2024. AFTER A RECENT GO AHEAD MESSAGE
FROM MARK CUBAN I WAS DECLARED CEO OF PROJECT MELO AND THREE
YEARS LATER I'M AMBASSADOR. EVERYTHING TURNED OUT THREE
MONTHS LATER IN THE SAME INSTANT I GET TO KNOW LOUISA
MAC AS A FRIEND AND ARTIST AND 2014 KARMA HAS CONNECTED
WITH ME AS A PARTNER IN CRIME. >> SO I STAND BY BOTH PERSON
WISER TRICKS TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE FOR MY ROLE
AND HOPEFULLY WE COULD BECOME FRIENDS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
COME ON. >> AND GOOD AFTERNOON
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS HARLOW PIPPIN JR.
I'M A DISTRICT TWO RESIDENT AND MEMBER OF THE PUBLIC BANK
COALITION. I'M ALSO HERE TO SPEAK
IN SUPPORT OF THE GREEN PUBLIC BANK RESOLUTION.
THIS IS A REALLY INSPIRING INITIATIVE THAT WILL HAVE THE
POTENTIAL TO DO A LOT FOR THE CITY IN TERMS OF MAKING
INVESTMENTS IN GREEN ENERGY, SOCIAL HOUSING AND SMALL
BUSINESSES AND A LOT OF OTHER PRIORITIES THAT WE SHARE.
I THINK ACROSS THE POLITICAL SPECTRUM WE'VE SEEN PROVEN
SUCCESS OF THE PUBLIC BANK MODEL AROUND THE WORLD.
AND I THINK THIS IS A GREAT OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO FOLLOW
THAT APPROACH AND BEGIN MAKING THESE INVESTMENTS TO MAKE SAN
FRANCISCO BETTER FOR ALL RESIDENTS.
SO I ENCOURAGE ALL OF YOU TO PLEASE SUPPORT THIS RESOLUTION
AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO KRISTEN EVANS.
I AM ALSO HERE TO SPEAK ABOUT THE RESOLUTION ON THE PUBLIC
BANK. SO THE PUBLIC BANK COALITION
STARTED IN SAN FRANCISCO I THINK IN 2018.
I WAS LATE TO THE PARTY. I JOINED IN 2023 WHEN WE WERE
FORMING THE REINVESTMENT WORKING GROUP AND THAT WAS
COMPRISED OF COMMUNITY EXPERTS OF WHICH I WAS REPRESENTING
SMALL BUSINESS AS WELL AS BANKING AND FINANCIAL EXPERTS.
>> AND IT WAS A REALLY INTERESTING TIME.
IT WAS DURING THE TIME WHEN SILICON VALLEY BANK COLLAPSED.
IT WAS AN INTERESTING MOMENT WHEN WE WERE CONTEMPLATING
GOVERNANCE STRUCTURE AND THE WAY TO ESTABLISH GOOD
GOVERNANCE PRACTICES TO ENSURE A ROBUST PUBLIC BANK.
WE LOOKED AT MODELS THAT OF OTHER SUCCESSFUL BANKS ACROSS
THE COUNTRY AND ALSO ABROAD IN PARTICULAR I WAS GOING TO
NOTE FOR SMALL BUSINESSES THE LONGEST RUNNING PUBLIC BANKING
IN THE UNITED STATES THE BANK OF NORTH DAKOTA WHICH IS OVER
100 YEARS OLD, MADE HEADLINES AROUND THE PANDEMIC BECAUSE
THEY WERE MOST THE MOST SUCCESSFUL STATE AT GETTING THE
HIGHEST PPE LOAN RATES OUT TO THEIR SMALL BUSINESS SMALL
BUSINESSES AND SPECIFICALLY THEY HAD THE HIGHEST DOLLAR PER
CAPITA FOR BY FOR EACH SMALL BUSINESS WORKER.
AND IT WAS THROUGH THEIR INFRASTRUCTURE AND PARTNERSHIP
WITH LOCAL COMMUNITY BANKS THAT THEY WERE ABLE TO BE MUCH MORE
SUCCESSFUL AT A TIME WHEN IN SAN FRANCISCO SMALL
BUSINESSES WERE STRUGGLING TO ACCESS CAPITAL AND WELLS FARGO
WAS REALLY HAD FROZEN PROCESSING PPE LOANS.
SO THERE'S REALLY SOME GOOD ARGUMENTS FOR GOOD SOUND POLICY
FOR CREATING A METHOD FOR US TO HAVE A BANKING ESTABLISHMENT
BOTH TO SUPPORT SMALL BUSINESSES BUT ALSO AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND ALL THE OTHER WONDERFUL PROJECTS THAT WERE
MENTIONED INCLUDING GREENING AND ENVIRONMENTAL EFFORTS.
>> THANKS SO MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> OKAY, I'D LIKE TO TALK ABOUT CLIMATE CHANGE.
WINTER, SPRING, SUMMER, FALL. THERE YOU GO.
CLIMATE CHANGE. >> THE REST IS ALL A LIE.
IT'S COMMUNIST BIAS. >> NOW I'D ALSO LIKE TO TALK
ABOUT JOSEPH. OKAY.
REMEMBER HIM? JACOB'S FAVORITE SON.
AND SO HE COMES IN AND PHARAOH SAYS THERE WAS ON THE BANK OF
THE RIVER KEEFE RAISED THE BANK OF THE RIVER AND HE SAW SEVEN
COWS COME OUT. >> AND JOSEPH TELLS HIM THAT
THOSE SEVEN COWS ARE SEVEN GOOD YEARS AND THE SKINNY ONES AT
EIGHT THE FAT ONES AND WE'RE STILL SKINNY REPRESENT SEVEN
YEARS. OKAY.
NOW FAST FORWARD AROUND 1380 YEARS TO DANIEL'S DAYS A
SIMILAR CHARACTER. THEY'RE BOTH CAPTIVES IN A
FOREIGN LAND. THEY BOTH INTERPRET DREAMS.
>> NOW HE SEES IN THE 12TH AND LAST CHAPTER ON THE BANK OF
THE RIVER. KEY PHRASE BANK OF THE RIVER.
BANK OF THE RIVER. ONE ANGEL.
ANOTHER ANGEL ON THE BANK OF THE RIVER.
THIRD ANGEL ON TOP OF THE RIVER IS ASKED BY THE OTHER ANGEL ON
THE BANK OF THE RIVER HOW LONG WILL IT BE TO THE END OF THESE
WONDERS HE RAISES HIS RIGHT AND LEFT HAND TO HEAVEN
AND SWEARS BY HIM THAT LIVES FOREVER.
THAT IT'LL BE IN THREE AND A HALF YEARS NO ANIMALS COME OUT
BUT A STATEMENT OF TIME WHICH IS OF COURSE HALF OF SEVEN
YEARS THREE AND A HALF YEARS IS GIVEN THAT THEY NEED AN
INTERPRETATION OF OKAY NOW TO MAKE THINGS MORE COMPLEX, HE
SAYS THERE'S AN ADDITIONAL 30 DAYS AFTER THE THREE AND A HALF
YEARS AND THERE'S GOING TO BE THE ABOMINATION OF DESOLATION
TO THE TAKING AWAY THE DAILY SACRIFICE.
THAT'S THE THAT'S THAT'S THE MYSTERY AND THEN THERE'S AN
ADDITIONAL 45 DAYS. OKAY.
AND IT'S STRANGE BECAUSE THE LUNAR DIFFERENCE IN 45 YEARS IS
70 WEEKS. SO THESE 45 DAYS BRING US TO
THE END BECAUSE HE TELLS DANIEL TO GO HIS WAY CAUSE HE'S GOING
TO DIE AND THEN BE RESURRECTED AT THE END OF THE 45 DAYS.
THINK ABOUT THAT. PUT THAT IN YOUR PIPE AND SMOKE
IT HEAVY THE BIBLE HEY, DO WE HAVE ANOTHER SPEAKER?
JESUS. ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS?
>> OKAY. COME FORWARD, SIR, BEFORE YOU
BEGIN IF THERE ARE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO
HAVEN'T YET SPOKEN AND YOU WOULD LIKE TO THIS AFTERNOON
PLEASE STAND IN LINE OR ELSE THIS WILL BE OUR LAST SPEAKER.
>> WELCOME, SIR. MY NAME IS RICHARD S.G.
PETERSON. I LIVE IN WAY VALLEY OF SAN
FRANCISCO AND I FOLLOW THE NEWS AND I AM VERY DISTURBED BY THE
NEWS. ORDINARILY I'D TALK ABOUT
PARCEL TAXES BECAUSE I THINK THAT THE MAYORS STAND ON PARCEL
TAXES IS A BIT SKEWED FOR DOWNTOWN AND IT DOES NOT TAKE
THE INTEREST OF HOMEOWNERS HOME OWNERS INTO CONSIDERATION.
>> BUT TODAY I'D LIKE TO TALK ABOUT A COUPLE OF THINGS THAT
I'VE READ IN THE NEWS AND THE ONE IS MARC BENIOFF.
HE OF COURSE HAS BEEN IN THE NEWS FOR INSIGHT IN THE DONALD
TRUMP TO PERHAPS ALMOST IMMEDIATELY BRING TROOPS INTO
OUR CITY. NOW THIS WAS KIND OF A GAFFE
THAT HE WALKED BACK A LITTLE BIT BUT NOT REALLY.
HE IS A PROFESSED REPUBLICAN NOW AFTER BEING A DEMOCRAT FOR
MANY YEARS AND TAKING THE SERVICES OF MANY YEARS NOT TO
SERVICES BUT TAKING THE PROVIDING SERVICE HE WHO WAS
VERY GENEROUS HE IS AN ENTERPRISE SOFTWARE DEVELOPER
FORMERLY WE HAD IBM IF YOU WANT TO CHECK ME OUT I'VE BEEN
IN THIS BUSINESS FOR 50 YEARS BUT THAT'S NOT THE REAL THING.
HE'S JUST ONE OF THE BIG PROS THAT ARE RUNNING THE SHOW.
WHAT I REALLY WANT TO TALK ABOUT IS THE DISTURBING THING
THAT I READ IN THE PAPER ABOUT MAYOR LURIE AND THE NO BID
CONTRACT THAT HAS BEEN BROUGHT UP AND I REALIZE THAT THERE HAS
BEEN TALK ABOUT THAT IN THE BOARD AT THIS PARTICULAR TIME
AND THE ONLY APPARENT DEFENDER HAS BEEN ONE OF OUR SUPERVISORS
THAT IS ACTUALLY A DEMOCRATIC SOCIALIST.
>> INTERESTING YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR
FOUR ADOPTION COMMITTEE REFERENCED AGENDA ITEMS 54
THROUGH 58 ITEMS 54 THROUGH 58 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE. >> I THINK THAT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MAY WANT TO FOR SOMETHING YEAH YET.
57 PLEASE. >> AND I WANT TO SEVER 54
AND MADAM CLERK COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE BALANCE OF THE
ITEMS ON ITEMS 50 556 AND 58? SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR EITHER ARE TENNIS WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK COULD YOU
PLEASE CALL ITEM 54 ITEM 54 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
CELEBRATE DIWALI ON OCTOBER 20TH 2025 IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND HONORING THE SOUTH ASIAN
COMMUNITY FOR ITS ENDURING CONTRIBUTION TIONS TO THE CITY
AND AND THE CITY REAFFIRMS ITS COMMITMENT TO PROMOTING EQUITY
,INCLUSION AND CULTURAL CELEBRATION FOR ALL SAN
FRANCISCANS. THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
I PULLED THIS ITEM BECAUSE I WANTED TO THANK AND ANGELE
REMEY FOR COMING BY AND TALKING TO US A BIT ABOUT DIWALI ALSO
TO CONGRATULATE HER AND PARIVAR BE AT BAY AREA ON YOUR NEW HOME
AT 837 TURK. >> DIWALI IS OF COURSE MORE
THAN JUST A CELEBRATION OF LIGHT SWEETS AND FIREWORKS.
IT'S ALSO A CELEBRATION OF THE TRIUMPH OF LIGHT OVER DARKNESS
GOOD OVER EVIL AND HOPE OVER DESPAIR.
ACROSS INDIA AND AROUND THE WORLD MILLIONS OF PEOPLE LIGHT
DAHLIAS DECORATE THEIR HOMES AND COME TOGETHER WITH FAMILY
AND FRIENDS TO MARK THE JOYOUS OCCASION IT'S A CELEBRATION OF
RENEWAL OF LIFE, OF RELATIONSHIPS AND OF PURPOSE
AND IT INVITES US TO REFLECT ON THE PAST YEAR OR TO LET GO OF
NEGATIVITY AND TO WELCOME NEW BEGINNINGS WITH OPEN HEARTS
AND OPEN MINDS. I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES
FOR THEIR UNANIMOUS CO-SPONSORSHIP AND THANK CALVIN
IN MY OFFICE FOR HIS WORK ON THE RESOLUTION AND AND WITH
THAT I'M SURE THERE ARE NO OBJECTIONS.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 57 ITEM 57 RESOLUTION TO
RECOGNIZE OCTOBER 2025 AS DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AWARENESS
MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND THANK
YOU TO ALL MY EVERY SINGLE ONE OF MY COLLEAGUES FOR
CO-SPONSORING THIS LEGISLATION. AND TO THOSE OF YOU WHO
ATTENDED THE RALLY EARLIER, I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE CONSORT AND BEVERLY UPTON WHO JUST
SPOKE AT THE OFFICE OF VICTIMS RIGHTS.
I SEE DIRECTOR IVY LEE AND BOBBY LOPEZ HERE ALONG WITH
SAM HOGAN FROM SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD'S OFFICE AND ALSO TRACY
BROWN GALLARDO IN SUPERVISOR WALTON'S OFFICE AND OTHERS WHO
SUPPORTED THIS EFFORT ALONG THE WAY WE HAVE SUCH A LONG WAY TO
GO. >> COLLEAGUES, I JUST WANT TO
THANK ALL OF THE SERVICE PROVIDERS AND ADVOCATES
ESPECIALLY THE SURVIVORS WHO CONTINUE TO SHED A LIGHT ON
THIS ISSUE AND FIGHT FEARLESSLY AND WITH COURAGE.
IT TAKES COURAGE TO SURVIVE AND THRIVE.
I AM A SURVIVOR OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AND ABUSE ALONG WITH
MY MOTHER AND SISTERS. THERE ARE SO MANY OF US WHO
HAVE LIVED THROUGH IT AND ARE AT RISK OR ARE AT RISK OF IT
AND WE NEED TO DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO INVEST IN THE RESOURCES
TO PREVENT AND TO UPLIFT SURVIVORS.
THIS MEANS HOUSING IT MEANS HEALTH CARE, IT MEANS SERVICES,
MENTAL HEALTH RESOURCES AND WRAPAROUND CARE TO
GENERATION STRATEGIES EVERYTHING WE CAN TO UPLIFT
PEOPLE. WE MUST DO AND WE HAVE TO DO IT
WHEN IT COUNTS AT BUDGET TIME. IT BREAKS MY HEART TO KNOW THAT
WE ARE SLIPPING BACKWARDS IN OUR CITY BACKWARDS AS
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE IS ON THE RISE LOCALLY AND NATIONALLY
DURING A TIME WHEN OUR BASIC FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS ARE UNDER
ATTACK. >> AGGRAVATED DOMESTIC ASSAULT
MAKES UP 50% OF DV INCIDENTS IN SAN FRANCISCO UP FROM 35%
IN 2019. WE MUST COMMIT TO DOING MORE
IN WITHOUT BEFORE I VOTE. BEFORE WE VOTE I WANT TO MAKE A
MOTION TO PRESENT A MINOR BUT MEANINGFUL AMENDMENT TO THE
RESOLUTION ON PAGE TWO PLEASE LINE SEVEN THROUGH EIGHT TO
REFLECT THE UPDATED THEME FOR THIS YEAR WHICH IS LEAD WITH
COURAGE A CALL TO ACTION AND IN A WAY TO HONOR THE STRENGTH OF
SURVIVORS AND THE IMPORTANCE OF OUR OWN ACCOUNTABILITY.
AND I HAVE CIRCULATED THIS AMENDMENT AMONG ALL OF MY
COLLEAGUES. THANK YOU.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR, WE HAVE A
MOTION TO AMEND THE RESOLUTION. IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY
CHAN COLLEAGUES? I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT
AMENDMENT WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE THE RESOLUTION AS AMENDED
AND THEN I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED RESOLUTION.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE RESOLUTION THE AMENDED RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND THEN
MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS I HAVE
NONE TO REPORT. >> MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU
PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM? TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR THE LATE MS. KAREN PEARCE
ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR THE LATE MR. HECTOR
WILLIAMS ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND MOVED BY
THE PRESIDENT TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR THE LATE MR. ARLO SMITH ON BEHALF OF
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR THE LATE MR. BEANO'S BUDDHA TURKEY ON
BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MANDEL FOR THE LATE MISS MAJOR GRIFFIN
GRACIE MR. MARK RENE AND MR. TERRENCE ALLEN.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I THINK THAT BRINGS
US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA. MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY
FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY AND WE ARE ADJOURNED